{
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "Translate: Trēs equī pulchrī vōbīs sunt.",
        "options": [
          "You have three beautiful horses.",
          "Three beautiful horses were taken from you.",
          "The three beautiful horses were for you.",
          "You need three beautiful horses."
        ],
        "correct_answer": "You have three beautiful horses."
      },
      {
        "question": "What rhetorical device is present in the following sentence? Titus plūs vīnī, plūs cibī, plūs pecūniae poposcit.",
        "options": [
          "simile",
          "tricolon",
          "polysyndeton",
          "chiasmus"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "tricolon"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who were the nine daughters of Mnemosyne, who brought inspiration to poets and other artists?",
        "options": [
          "Muses",
          "Graces",
          "Harpies",
          "Fates"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Muses"
      },
      {
        "question": "What island, home to the ancient Minoans and the legendary palace of King Minos at Knossos, lies to the southeast of mainland Greece?",
        "options": [
          "Sicily",
          "Sardinia",
          "Crete",
          "Cyprus"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Crete"
      },
      {
        "question": "What emperor, born in Spain, extended the empire through his conquests in Dacia and later was said to have adopted his soon-to-be successor Hadrian only a few days before his death?",
        "options": [
          "Claudius",
          "Vespasian",
          "Trajan",
          "Constantine"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Trajan"
      },
      {
        "question": "During the Roman Republic, what magistrate in the cursus honōrum acted as a judge?",
        "options": [
          "aedile",
          "tribune",
          "quaestor",
          "praetor"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "praetor"
      },
      {
        "question": "Oreads, Dryads, Nereads, and Oceanids were all types of",
        "options": [
          "nymphs",
          "Gorgons",
          "centaurs",
          "Sirens"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "nymphs"
      },
      {
        "question": "Julius Caesar was assassinated in 44 BCE, which is what year in AUC?",
        "options": [
          "753 AUC",
          "710 AUC",
          "553 AUC",
          "465 AUC"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "710 AUC"
      },
      {
        "question": "Identify the figure of speech in the following sentence: Senātor īrātus exclāmāvit, “Hoc nōn audiam, nōn patiar, certē nōn tolerābō!”",
        "options": [
          "personification",
          "antithesis",
          "tricolon",
          "oxymoron"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "tricolon"
      },
      {
        "question": "What Silver Age Roman author wrote letters which include an eyewitness account of the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius and questioned the emperor Trajan about Christians in his province?",
        "options": [
          "Pliny the Younger",
          "Livy",
          "Tacitus",
          "Marcus Aurelius"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Pliny the Younger"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which notable Roman helped lead the assassination of Julius Caesar and, together with his close associate Cassius, was defeated at the Battle of Philippi by Mark Antony and Octavian?",
        "options": [
          "Pompey",
          "Clodius",
          "Brutus",
          "Crassus"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Brutus"
      },
      {
        "question": "What river was first crossed by the Romans on a bridge built by Julius Caesar and essentially served later as the boundary between the Roman Empire and Germany?",
        "options": [
          "Tiber",
          "Rhine",
          "Rubicon",
          "Po"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Rhine"
      },
      {
        "question": "What class of Roman society, in an effort to gain rights from the patricians, would occasionally withdraw from the city and refuse to work until they gained such benefits as written laws in the Twelve Tables, representation by the tribunes, and a share in the consulship?",
        "options": [
          "plēbēs",
          "augurēs",
          "equitēs",
          "pontificēs"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "plēbēs"
      },
      {
        "question": "What literary device can be found in the following quotation: Quī illīus culpā cecidit velut prātī ultimī flōs?",
        "options": [
          "anaphora",
          "hendiadys",
          "simile",
          "zeugma"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "simile"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which emperor was born in Spain in 76 CE, was known for his fondness of Greek culture, and built a defensive wall in Britain that can still be seen today?",
        "options": [
          "Antoninus Pius",
          "Hadrian",
          "Marcus Aurelius",
          "Trajan"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Hadrian"
      },
      {
        "question": "Give the scansion pattern for the first four feet of this line from Sulpicia: Grātum est, sēcūrus multum quod iam tibi dē mē.",
        "options": [
          "DSDD",
          "SSDS",
          "DSSD",
          "SSSS"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "SSSS"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which character in mythology incurred the wrath of Venus and had to perform four labors before being able to marry her beloved Cupid?",
        "options": [
          "Eurydice",
          "Hero",
          "Psyche",
          "Thisbe"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Psyche"
      },
      {
        "question": "What philosophy, practiced by Cato the Younger, Seneca, and Marcus Aurelius, believed that one ought to live their lives virtuously, regardless of what fate and fortune might bring?",
        "options": [
          "Stoicism",
          "Epicureanism",
          "Pythagoreanism",
          "Cynicism"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Stoicism"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which granddaughter of Agrippa was both a wife of the emperor Claudius and the mother of the emperor Nero?",
        "options": [
          "Livia",
          "Drusilla",
          "Agrippina",
          "Antonia"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Agrippina"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which daughter of Priam and Hecuba foretold the destruction of Troy but was not believed?",
        "options": [
          "Andromache",
          "Briseis",
          "Cassandra",
          "Penthesilea"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Cassandra"
      },
      {
        "question": "What would a character in a play by Plautus be doing if they said, “Salvus sīs!”?",
        "options": [
          "insulting you",
          "questioning you",
          "complimenting you",
          "greeting you"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "greeting you"
      },
      {
        "question": "What is the term for the linguistic phenomenon whereby words lose a full syllable; e.g. amāvisse → amāsse?",
        "options": [
          "metathesis",
          "syncopation",
          "ablation",
          "elision"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "syncopation"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which of the following words is a monoptote?",
        "options": [
          "fas",
          "nihil",
          "glōs",
          "fors"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "glōs"
      },
      {
        "question": "The pronominal forms nostrī and vestrī are found exclusively with what use of the genitive?",
        "options": [
          "Specification",
          "Partitive",
          "Possession",
          "Objective"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "Objective"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which of the following can NOT be a locative ending?",
        "options": [
          "-īs",
          "-e",
          "-ī",
          "-um"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "-um"
      },
      {
        "question": "What syntactic function replaces the future tense of subjunctive clauses?",
        "options": [
          "periphrasis",
          "present subjunctive",
          "gerunds",
          "infinitives"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "periphrasis"
      },
      {
        "question": "What syntactic anomaly is shared by the words propinquus, surdus, and alacer?",
        "options": [
          "lacking comparative",
          "lacking superlative",
          "lacking adverbial forms",
          "they expect the dative"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "lacking superlative"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which of the following is NOT an adjectival ending appended to nouns?",
        "options": [
          "-ālis",
          "-īcius",
          "-ōsus",
          "these are all acceptable"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "these are all acceptable"
      },
      {
        "question": "Future Less Vivid conditionals contain verbs in what tense and mood?",
        "options": [
          "future indicative",
          "present indicative",
          "present subjunctive",
          "none of these"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "present subjunctive"
      },
      {
        "question": "What facet of Indo-European languages remains in Latin, but only in select words like reperio?",
        "options": [
          "reduplication",
          "ablation",
          "semi-deponent",
          "neutral passive"
        ],
        "correct_answer": "reduplication"
      },
      {
        "question": "What poet tailored the narrative of his epic the Aeneid to glorify Rome’s humble origins?",
        "options": ["Juvenal", "Statius", "Vergil", "Martial"],
        "correct_answer": "Vergil"
      },
      {
        "question": "Ovid presumably died in what city, given his last known poem was about exile here?",
        "options": ["Athens", "Tomi", "Persepolis", "Gades"],
        "correct_answer": "Tomi"
      },
      {
        "question": "What poet was executed by Nero the same year as his uncle because they were both implicated in a conspiracy?",
        "options": ["Cornutus", "Lucan", "Caesius Bassus", "Polybius"],
        "correct_answer": "Lucan"
      },
      {
        "question": "What rhetorical masterpiece by Cicero was a four-parter unmasking a scheme against the government?",
        "options": ["In Catilinam", "Pro Lege Manilia", "In Verrem", "Pro Archia Poeta"],
        "correct_answer": "In Catilinam"
      },
      {
        "question": "Whose historical research focused on crises of the Roman state such as the Jugurthine War?",
        "options": ["Sallust", "Seneca the Elder", "Panaetius", "Agrippa"],
        "correct_answer": "Sallust"
      },
      {
        "question": "What foreign people is effectively the antagonist of Naevius’ historical epic?",
        "options": ["The Spartans", "The Persians", "The Carthaginians", "The Etruscans"],
        "correct_answer": "The Carthaginians"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who made up the pseudonym ‘Lesbia’ as a reference to the eminent Greek poet Sappho?",
        "options": ["Catullus", "Clodius", "Fulvius", "Rufus"],
        "correct_answer": "Catullus"
      },
      {
        "question": "Julius Caesar described his battles against Vercingetorix for control of modern France in which work?",
        "options": ["De Bello Civili", "De Bello Gallico", "Bellum Alexandrinum", "Bellum Hispaniense"],
        "correct_answer": "De Bello Gallico"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which play by Terence has a title referring to the two brothers who are the center of the plot?",
        "options": ["Andria", "Adelphoi", "Phormio", "Eunuchus"],
        "correct_answer": "Adelphoi"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which philosophical ideology was the choice of the poet Lucretius?",
        "options": ["Stoicism", "Epicureanism", "Cynicism", "Neo-Platonism"],
        "correct_answer": "Epicureanism"
      },
      {
        "question": "What genre Fabula were all the known plays of Plautus?",
        "options": ["Praetexta", "Cothurnata", "Crepidata", "Palliata"],
        "correct_answer": "Palliata"
      },
      {
        "question": "What early Roman literary figure also fought at the battle of Thermopylae?",
        "options": ["Polybius", "Fabius Pictor", "Naevius", "Cato the Elder"],
        "correct_answer": "Cato the Elder"
      },
      {
        "question": "What patron and connoisseur of good poetry bankrolled Horace’s Epodes?",
        "options": ["Laelius", "Maecenas", "Messalla Corvinus", "Memmius"],
        "correct_answer": "Maecenas"
      },
      {
        "question": "A translation and continuation of Eusebius’ Chronicon remarks that Lucretius died of a love potion overdose and that Cicero emended the De Rerum Natura. Who wrote this translation and chose to include such information?",
        "options": ["Jerome", "Augustine", "Juvenal", "Cicero"],
        "correct_answer": "Jerome"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which of the following works was NOT a work of Tacitus?",
        "options": ["Historia Augusta", "Annales", "Agricola", "Dialogus de Oratoribus"],
        "correct_answer": "Historia Augusta"
      },
      {
        "question": "What kind of fish is the focus of Juvenal’s fourth Satire?",
        "options": ["Trout", "Mullet", "Shark", "Turbot"],
        "correct_answer": "Turbot"
      },
      {
        "question": "Where did Martial die?",
        "options": ["Bilbilis", "Rome", "Alexandria", "An unknown town"],
        "correct_answer": "Bilbilis"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which character in the Satyricon is an elderly poet who recites a poem about the fall of Troy to the other characters?",
        "options": ["Encolpius", "Giton", "Eumolpus", "Agamemnon"],
        "correct_answer": "Eumolpus"
      },
      {
        "question": "What work by Pliny the Elder cites over a hundred different ancient authors?",
        "options": ["Naturalis Historia", "Epistulae", "Panegyricus", "Studiosus"],
        "correct_answer": "Naturalis Historia"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who self-flatteringly called himself the ‘Roman Callimachus,’ but was less flatteringly called an ‘aping Callimachus’ by Horace?",
        "options": ["Cinna", "Asinius Pollio", "Ovid", "Propertius"],
        "correct_answer": "Propertius"
      },
      {
        "question": "What poet tailored the narrative of his epic the Aeneid to glorify Rome’s humble origins?",
        "options": ["Juvenal", "Statius", "Vergil", "Martial"],
        "correct_answer": "Vergil"
      },
      {
        "question": "Ovid presumably died in what city, given his last known poem was about exile here?",
        "options": ["Athens", "Tomi", "Persepolis", "Gades"],
        "correct_answer": "Tomi"
      },
      {
        "question": "What poet was executed by Nero the same year as his uncle because they were both implicated in a conspiracy?",
        "options": ["Cornutus", "Lucan", "Caesius Bassus", "Polybius"],
        "correct_answer": "Lucan"
      },
      {
        "question": "What rhetorical masterpiece by Cicero was a four-parter unmasking a scheme against the government?",
        "options": ["In Catilinam", "Pro Lege Manilia", "In Verrem", "Pro Archia Poeta"],
        "correct_answer": "In Catilinam"
      },
      {
        "question": "Whose historical research focused on crises of the Roman state such as the Jugurthine War?",
        "options": ["Sallust", "Seneca the Elder", "Panaetius", "Agrippa"],
        "correct_answer": "Sallust"
      },
      {
        "question": "What foreign people is effectively the antagonist of Naevius’ historical epic?",
        "options": ["The Spartans", "The Persians", "The Carthaginians", "The Etruscans"],
        "correct_answer": "The Carthaginians"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who made up the pseudonym ‘Lesbia’ as a reference to the eminent Greek poet Sappho?",
        "options": ["Catullus", "Clodius", "Fulvius", "Rufus"],
        "correct_answer": "Catullus"
      },
      {
        "question": "Julius Caesar described his battles against Vercingetorix for control of modern France in which work?",
        "options": ["De Bello Civili", "De Bello Gallico", "Bellum Alexandrinum", "Bellum Hispaniense"],
        "correct_answer": "De Bello Gallico"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which play by Terence has a title referring to the two brothers who are the center of the plot?",
        "options": ["Andria", "Adelphoi", "Phormio", "Eunuchus"],
        "correct_answer": "Adelphoi"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which philosophical ideology was the choice of the poet Lucretius?",
        "options": ["Stoicism", "Epicureanism", "Cynicism", "Neo-Platonism"],
        "correct_answer": "Epicureanism"
      },
      {
        "question": "What genre Fabula were all the known plays of Plautus?",
        "options": ["Praetexta", "Cothurnata", "Crepidata", "Palliata"],
        "correct_answer": "Palliata"
      },
      {
        "question": "What early Roman literary figure also fought at the battle of Thermopylae?",
        "options": ["Polybius", "Fabius Pictor", "Naevius", "Cato the Elder"],
        "correct_answer": "Cato the Elder"
      },
      {
        "question": "What patron and connoisseur of good poetry bankrolled Horace’s Epodes?",
        "options": ["Laelius", "Maecenas", "Messalla Corvinus", "Memmius"],
        "correct_answer": "Maecenas"
      },
      {
        "question": "A translation and continuation of Eusebius’ Chronicon remarks that Lucretius died of a love potion overdose and that Cicero emended the De Rerum Natura. Who wrote this translation and chose to include such information?",
        "options": ["Jerome", "Augustine", "Juvenal", "Cicero"],
        "correct_answer": "Jerome"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which of the following works was NOT a work of Tacitus?",
        "options": ["Historia Augusta", "Annales", "Agricola", "Dialogus de Oratoribus"],
        "correct_answer": "Historia Augusta"
      },
      {
        "question": "What kind of fish is the focus of Juvenal’s fourth Satire?",
        "options": ["Trout", "Mullet", "Shark", "Turbot"],
        "correct_answer": "Turbot"
      },
      {
        "question": "Where did Martial die?",
        "options": ["Bilbilis", "Rome", "Alexandria", "An unknown town"],
        "correct_answer": "Bilbilis"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which character in the Satyricon is an elderly poet who recites a poem about the fall of Troy to the other characters?",
        "options": ["Encolpius", "Giton", "Eumolpus", "Agamemnon"],
        "correct_answer": "Eumolpus"
      },
      {
        "question": "What work by Pliny the Elder cites over a hundred different ancient authors?",
        "options": ["Naturalis Historia", "Epistulae", "Panegyricus", "Studiosus"],
        "correct_answer": "Naturalis Historia"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who self-flatteringly called himself the ‘Roman Callimachus,’ but was less flatteringly called an ‘aping Callimachus’ by Horace?",
        "options": ["Cinna", "Asinius Pollio", "Ovid", "Propertius"],
        "correct_answer": "Propertius"
      },
      {
        "question": "Whose system of government had two Augusti and two Caesars?",
        "options": ["Diocletian", "Constantius", "Gallienus", "Maximian"],
        "correct_answer": "Diocletian"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who bequeathed Pergamum to Rome?",
        "options": ["Nicomedes III", "Attalus III", "Ptolemy III", "Prusias III"],
        "correct_answer": "Attalus III"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which king of Rome sacked Alba Longa?",
        "options": ["Servius Tullius", "Tullus Hostilius", "Ancus Martius", "Tarquinius Priscus"],
        "correct_answer": "Tullus Hostilius"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who was the primary political opponent of Sulla?",
        "options": ["C. Gracchus", "Gn. Pompey", "C. Marius", "Cato the Elder"],
        "correct_answer": "C. Marius"
      },
      {
        "question": "What fellow tribune did Tib. Gracchus depose for vetoing Tiberius' agrarian reforms?",
        "options": ["Claudius", "Saturninus", "Metellus", "Octavius"],
        "correct_answer": "Octavius"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which Roman general did NOT fight against Mithridates the Great?",
        "options": ["Sulla", "Marius", "Pompey", "Lucullus"],
        "correct_answer": "Marius"
      },
      {
        "question": "What Roman city did Hadrian found on the site of the destroyed city of Jerusalem?",
        "options": ["Aelia Capitolina", "Adrianople", "Agrippinensis", "Caesarea Maritima"],
        "correct_answer": "Aelia Capitolina"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who was executed for treason in A.D. 48?",
        "options": ["Sejanus", "Messalina", "St. Paul", "Agrippina the Elder"],
        "correct_answer": "Messalina"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who was the last Roman political opponent of Constantine?",
        "options": ["Maxentius", "Licinius", "Maximinus", "Perennius"],
        "correct_answer": "Licinius"
      },
      {
        "question": "What emperor did Gn. Lentulus Gaetulicus try to overthrow?",
        "options": ["Caligula", "Tiberius", "Nero", "Claudius"],
        "correct_answer": "Caligula"
      },
      {
        "question": "For which emperor did Avidius Cassius capture Edessa, Nisibus and Ctesiphon?",
        "options": ["Domitian", "Trajan", "M. Aurelius", "Hadrian"],
        "correct_answer": "M. Aurelius"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who led the Decemviri in writing the Twelve Tables?",
        "options": ["T. Genucius", "T. Valerius Publicola", "Appius Claudius", "Sp. Tarpeius"],
        "correct_answer": "Appius Claudius"
      },
      {
        "question": "How many curiae were in the original Comitia Curiata?",
        "options": ["30", "40", "50", "60"],
        "correct_answer": "50"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which political unit was NOT allied with Rome in the war against Antiochus III?",
        "options": ["Macedonia", "Carthage", "Aetolian League", "Achaean League"],
        "correct_answer": "Carthage"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who was the Roman commander killed at Lake Trasimene?",
        "options": ["Aemilius Paulus", "Terentius Varro", "C. Flaminius", "Currius Dentatus"],
        "correct_answer": "C. Flaminius"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who in a chariot ran over her father, the King of Rome?",
        "options": ["Tullia", "Hersilia", "Tanaquil", "Egeria"],
        "correct_answer": "Tullia"
      },
      {
        "question": "Where was Zenobia's capital?",
        "options": ["Babylon", "Antioch", "Ctesiphon", "Palmyra"],
        "correct_answer": "Palmyra"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which tribe captured Rome in the 5th century B.C.?",
        "options": ["Haedui", "Senones", "Ebrones", "Bellovaci"],
        "correct_answer": "Senones"
      },
      {
        "question": "What location was home to Apollo’s most famous oracle?",
        "options": ["Delphi", "Dodona", "Claros", "Delos"],
        "correct_answer": "Delphi"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who was guarded by Argus Panoptes after Zeus turned her into a cow?",
        "options": ["Hera", "Europa", "Io", "Alcmene"],
        "correct_answer": "Io"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who designed a cow costume for Pasiphae, made wax wings for Icarus, and engineered the Labyrinth?",
        "options": ["Daedalus", "Perdix", "Minos", "Trophonius"],
        "correct_answer": "Daedalus"
      },
      {
        "question": "What city was founded on the spot where Cadmus’s cow fell to rest?",
        "options": ["Boeotia", "Thebes", "Argos", "Athens"],
        "correct_answer": "Thebes"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who gave a sickle to her son Cronus so he could castrate her husband Uranus?",
        "options": ["Nyx", "Chaos", "Gaea", "Eos"],
        "correct_answer": "Gaea"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who patiently waited 20 years for the return of her husband Odysseus?",
        "options": ["Peisidice", "Penelope", "Persephone", "Proserpina"],
        "correct_answer": "Penelope"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who fled the burning city of Troy with his father Anchises to set out for Italy?",
        "options": ["Hector", "Aeneas", "Ascanius", "Odysseus"],
        "correct_answer": "Aeneas"
      },
      {
        "question": "What monster did Heracles resort to choking out since it had an invulnerable pelt?",
        "options": ["Erymanthian Boar", "Cerberus", "Cretan Bull", "Nemean Lion"],
        "correct_answer": "Nemean Lion"
      },
      {
        "question": "What son of Cronus and Philyra famously tutored Jason and Achilles?",
        "options": ["Linus", "Nestor", "Patroclus", "Chiron"],
        "correct_answer": "Chiron"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who was the burning brand that led to Troy’s demise by deeming Aphrodite the fairest?",
        "options": ["Hector", "Paris", "Aeneas", "Sarpedon"],
        "correct_answer": "Paris"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which of the following mythological figures did not visit the Underworld?",
        "options": ["Theseus", "Odysseus", "Perseus", "Aeneas"],
        "correct_answer": "Perseus"
      },
      {
        "question": "Although he was initially duped, Heracles managed to trick what Titan into holding the sky once more?",
        "options": ["Menoetius", "Epimetheus", "Prometheus", "Atlas"],
        "correct_answer": "Atlas"
      },
      {
        "question": "What Phrygian couple hospitably hosted Jupiter and Mercury and were made priests of their temple?",
        "options": ["Procris & Tereus", "Admetus & Alcestis", "Deucalion & Pyrrha", "Baucis & Philemon"],
        "correct_answer": "Baucis & Philemon"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who married the new king of Thebes after he defeated the Sphinx, not realizing he was her own son Oedipus?",
        "options": ["Antigone", "Laius", "Eurydice", "Jocasta"],
        "correct_answer": "Jocasta"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who eternally struggled in the Underworld to get a sip of water or a bite of food?",
        "options": ["Tantalus", "Ixion", "Sisyphus", "Tityus"],
        "correct_answer": "Tantalus"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who floated up on the island of Seriphos in a chest with her son Perseus?",
        "options": ["Alcmene", "Althaea", "Danae", "Aethra"],
        "correct_answer": "Danae"
      },
      {
        "question": "What Greek deity was known by an epithet meaning 'earthshaker'?",
        "options": ["Poseidon", "Zeus", "Hades", "Triton"],
        "correct_answer": "Poseidon"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who was abandoned on Naxos even after she helped Theseus navigate the Labyrinth with a ball of thread?",
        "options": ["Ariadne", "Phaedra", "Hippolyta", "Antiope"],
        "correct_answer": "Ariadne"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which of the following is not a herdsman of Odysseus?",
        "options": ["Melanthius", "Dolius", "Eumaeus", "Philoetius"],
        "correct_answer": "Dolius"
      },
      {
        "question": "Whose decapitated head still retained its power by turning seaweed into coral and men into stone?",
        "options": ["Medusa", "Echidna", "Phaea", "Medea"],
        "correct_answer": "Medusa"
      },
      {
        "question": "What horse did Bellerophon try to ride to Mount Olympus?",
        "options": ["Pegasus", "Xanthus", "Balius", "Arion"],
        "correct_answer": "Pegasus"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who unwittingly unleashed sorrows and diseases on humankind from her jar?",
        "options": ["Prometheus", "Panthous", "Pandora", "Pancratis"],
        "correct_answer": "Pandora"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which of the following is a subjunctive form of queo?",
        "options": ["quibis", "quiremus", "quibamus", "queunt"],
        "correct_answer": "quiremus"
      },
      {
        "question": "Under what syntactic category does the noun dicionis belong?",
        "options": ["triptote", "monoptote", "tetraptote", "indeclinable"],
        "correct_answer": "monoptote"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which of these prepositions does NOT take the Accusative?",
        "options": ["penes", "secundum", "ob", "absque"],
        "correct_answer": "absque"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which of the following does NOT belong grammatically?",
        "options": ["lepus", "vulpes", "pavo", "lupus"],
        "correct_answer": "pavo"
      },
      {
        "question": "What do all of the following have in common grammatically: quincunx, bes, deunx?",
        "options": ["They are all multiplicative", "They are all proportional", "They are all distributive", "They are all fractions"],
        "correct_answer": "They are all fractions"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which Spartan King co-ruled with Leonidas at the time of the latter’s death in 480 B.C.?",
        "options": ["Agis II", "Pausanias", "Leotychidas", "Theopompus"],
        "correct_answer": "Leotychidas"
      },
      {
        "question": "Whose Athenian’s law codes were so harsh they were said to have been written not in ink but in blood?",
        "options": ["Solon", "Cleisthenes", "Pisistratus", "Draco"],
        "correct_answer": "Draco"
      },
      {
        "question": "What son of Xenophon was said to have killed Epaminondas in single-handed combat in 362 B.C.?",
        "options": ["Pelopidas", "Agesilaus", "Gryllus", "Ephialtes"],
        "correct_answer": "Gryllus"
      },
      {
        "question": "At the end of the Dark Age circa 800 B.C., the Greeks adopted a new alphabet from what people?",
        "options": ["Phoenicians", "Minoans", "Mycenaeans", "Persians"],
        "correct_answer": "Phoenicians"
      },
      {
        "question": "After the fall of its monarchy, what aristocratic family ruled Corinth until 650 B.C.?",
        "options": ["Megaclids", "Achaemonids", "Bacchiads", "Penthilids"],
        "correct_answer": "Bacchiads"
      },
      {
        "question": "What city founded by Euboean city-states in 750 B.C. is traditionally called the first Greek colony?",
        "options": ["Croton", "Messana", "Cumae", "Syracuse"],
        "correct_answer": "Cumae"
      },
      {
        "question": "What Messenian hero sacrificed his mother in a failed attempt to save the city from the Spartans?",
        "options": ["Aristodemus", "Cypselus", "Lycurgus", "Pittacus"],
        "correct_answer": "Aristodemus"
      },
      {
        "question": "When were the Olympic Games traditionally held for the first time?",
        "options": ["776", "538", "800", "664"],
        "correct_answer": "776"
      },
      {
        "question": "The Amphictyonic League fought three Sacred Wars protecting what city?",
        "options": ["Sicyon", "Delphi", "Krisa", "Argos"],
        "correct_answer": "Delphi"
      },
      {
        "question": "When a prophecy told the Athenians they should ‘put their trust in the wooden walls,’ who interpreted this to mean they should build a fleet in 480 B.C.?",
        "options": ["Pericles", "Ephialtes", "Aristides", "Themistocles"],
        "correct_answer": "Themistocles"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who was assassinated in 514 B.C. by Harmodius and Aristogiton because he had slighted Harmodius’ sister?",
        "options": ["Hippias", "Pisistratus", "Hipparchus", "Solon"],
        "correct_answer": "Hipparchus"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who was the mother of Alexander the Great?",
        "options": ["Cleopatra", "Olympias", "Roxanne", "Berenice"],
        "correct_answer": "Olympias"
      },
      {
        "question": "What Athenian was elected strategos fifteen consecutive times from 444-429 B.C.?",
        "options": ["Pericles", "Aristides", "Pisistratus", "Cimon"],
        "correct_answer": "Pericles"
      },
      {
        "question": "A peace named after what Athenian ended the first 10-year period of The Peloponnesian War in 421 B.C.?",
        "options": ["Alcibiades", "Cleon", "Callias", "Nicias"],
        "correct_answer": "Nicias"
      },
      {
        "question": "What Persian king defeated the Spartans at Thermopylae in 480 B.C.?",
        "options": ["Darius I", "Xerxes", "Datis", "Mardonius"],
        "correct_answer": "Xerxes"
      },
      {
        "question": "What name was given to the Spartan assembly of all citizens over 30 who had served in the military?",
        "options": ["Gerousia", "Boule", "Ecclesia", "Apella"],
        "correct_answer": "Gerousia"
      },
      {
        "question": "What Athenian statesman went into voluntarily exile following his archonship of 594-593 B.C.?",
        "options": ["Solon", "Draco", "Cylon", "Aristides"],
        "correct_answer": "Solon"
      },
      {
        "question": "What Athenian statesman known as ‘The Just’ was tasked with keeping the Delian League’s finances?",
        "options": ["Xanthippus", "Pericles", "Aristides", "Cimon"],
        "correct_answer": "Aristides"
      },
      {
        "question": "According to tradition, how many Athenians were said to have perished at the Battle of Marathon?",
        "options": ["50", "192", "6", "2,000"],
        "correct_answer": "192"
      },
      {
        "question": "At what river did Alexander the Great’s army mutiny, ending his eastern campaign in 326 B.C.?",
        "options": ["Hyphasis", "Hydaspes", "Jhelum", "Indus"],
        "correct_answer": "Hyphasis"
      },
      {
        "question": "What Lydian king was told that if he attacked the Persians, a great empire would fall?",
        "options": ["Aristogoras", "Cyrus", "Croesus", "Cambyses"],
        "correct_answer": "Croesus"
      },
      {
        "question": "What political party was formed by Pisistratus in support of his on-and-off tyranny?",
        "options": ["the Coast", "the Plains", "the Hills", "the Walls"],
        "correct_answer": "the Hills"
      },
      {
        "question": "What was the term for Spartan governors who controlled Greece following the Peloponnesian War?",
        "options": ["neodamodes", "perioeci", "polemarch", "harmosts"],
        "correct_answer": "harmosts"
      },
      {
        "question": "What mythological group relentlessly pursued Orestes after he had killed his mother Clytemnestra?",
        "options": ["the Fates", "the Harpies", "the Furies", "the Sirens"],
        "correct_answer": "the Furies"
      },
      {
        "question": "What was the name of the bundle of rods surrounding an ax which is seen at the right? It symbolized the power of a Roman magistrate to inflict corporal and capital punishment.",
        "options": ["fascēs", "stilī", "tabellae", "strigilēs"],
        "correct_answer": "fascēs"
      },
      {
        "question": "The English words extend, contender, and tension come from the Latin word meaning to",
        "options": ["stretch", "roll", "lift", "remove"],
        "correct_answer": "stretch"
      },
      {
        "question": "What statesman, lawyer, and philosopher was considered Rome’s greatest orator in the first century BC?",
        "options": ["Marius", "Sulla", "Cicero", "Pompey"],
        "correct_answer": "Cicero"
      },
      {
        "question": "What mythological creature, eventually killed by Bellerophon, was a combination of a lion, goat, and snake?",
        "options": ["a centaur", "the Sphinx", "a satyr", "the Chimera"],
        "correct_answer": "the Chimera"
      },
      {
        "question": "When your teacher says “Cōnsīdite, omnēs!” at the beginning of class, she wants all the students to",
        "options": ["sit down", "pay attention", "pass forward their work", "open their books"],
        "correct_answer": "sit down"
      },
      {
        "question": "Usus, coemptio, and confarreatio all were types of Roman",
        "options": ["funerals", "triumphs", "weddings", "priesthoods"],
        "correct_answer": "weddings"
      },
      {
        "question": "What Latin motto means that teaching is the best way to learn something?",
        "options": ["memento mori", "crescit eundo", "ex nihilo nihil fit", "docendo discitur"],
        "correct_answer": "docendo discitur"
      },
      {
        "question": "What member of the First Triumvirate was defeated by Julius Caesar at the Battle of Pharsalus to end their civil war?",
        "options": ["Crassus", "Octavian", "Pompey", "Brutus"],
        "correct_answer": "Pompey"
      },
      {
        "question": "Clotho, Lachesis, and Atropos, who spun, measured, and cut the thread of life, were known as the",
        "options": ["Harpies", "Furies", "Fates", "Titans"],
        "correct_answer": "Fates"
      },
      {
        "question": "What place has five rivers, a field for the blessed, and a large abyss?",
        "options": ["Troy", "Mt. Olympus", "the Underworld", "Carthage"],
        "correct_answer": "the Underworld"
      },
      {
        "question": "What Roman senator was accused by Cicero of attempting a coup during his consulship in 63 BC?",
        "options": ["Marcus Antonius", "Lucius Sergius Catilina", "Gnaeus Pompeius", "Lucius Cornelius Sulla"],
        "correct_answer": "Lucius Sergius Catilina"
      },
      {
        "question": "During the Roman Republic, what government position was created to protect plebeians with its veto power?",
        "options": ["aedile", "tribune", "praetor", "consul"],
        "correct_answer": "tribune"
      },
      {
        "question": "What date did the Romans use to mark the approximate midpoint for each month?",
        "options": ["Kalends", "Nones", "Ides", "Fasti"],
        "correct_answer": "Ides"
      },
      {
        "question": "Scylla and Charybdis were believed to dwell between Italy and what land mass, which was also the Romans’ first province?",
        "options": ["Gallia", "Sicilia", "Crēta", "Hispānia"],
        "correct_answer": "Sicilia"
      },
      {
        "question": "What English phrase best represents the Latin expression suum cuique?",
        "options": ["No man is an island.", "Everyone is entitled to their own opinion.", "Say nothing except good about the dead.", "Take each day as it comes"],
        "correct_answer": "Everyone is entitled to their own opinion."
      },
      {
        "question": "Ā convīviō nōn sine multō cachinnō discessī! What figure of speech can be found in this sentence?",
        "options": ["metaphor", "personification", "asyndeton", "litotes"],
        "correct_answer": "litotes"
      },
      {
        "question": "Loquere, quaesō, lentius! Tōtam fābulam audīre cupiō! What does this Latin phrase translate to?",
        "options": ["Speak", "Planning to speak", "They spoke", "To speak"],
        "correct_answer": "Speak"
      },
      {
        "question": "Tullia plūs _____ poposcit.",
        "options": ["aqua", "aquae", "aquam", "aquīs"],
        "correct_answer": "aqua"
      },
      {
        "question": "What Roman emperor, the immediate successor of Trajan, incorporated architectural styles from his many travels in his villa, and built a defensive wall in Britain?",
        "options": ["Nero", "Tiberius", "Claudius", "Hadrian"],
        "correct_answer": "Hadrian"
      },
      {
        "question": "What is the meaning of the Latin phrase nil sub sole novum?",
        "options": ["There is nothing new under the sun.", "No news is good news.", "We are never alone.", "Not for ourselves alone are we born."],
        "correct_answer": "There is nothing new under the sun."
      },
      {
        "question": "What was the site of the famous oracle of Apollo where the god had killed the giant serpent Python?",
        "options": ["Carthage", "Sparta", "Delphi", "Athens"],
        "correct_answer": "Delphi"
      },
      {
        "question": "What Trojan warrior bid farewell to his wife Andromache and baby son Astyanax as he left for his final battle?",
        "options": ["Hector", "Priam", "Paris", "Aeneas"],
        "correct_answer": "Hector"
      },
      {
        "question": "What Latin phrase, expressed by Catullus in his poem to his dead brother, can be used to give a final farewell?",
        "options": ["Festīnā lentē!", "Avē atque valē!", "Ō tempora, Ō mōrēs!", "Sī tū valēs, valeō!"],
        "correct_answer": "Avē atque valē!"
      },
      {
        "question": "When Cicero said in his speech against Catiline that he would not dwell on Catiline’s crimes and then proceeded to do exactly that, he was employing the rhetorical device",
        "options": ["tricolon", "praeteritio", "anaphora", "polysyndeton"],
        "correct_answer": "praeteritio"
      },
      {
        "question": "What Silver Age Roman historian wrote about the emperors and corresponded with Pliny, among others?",
        "options": ["Tacitus", "Ovid", "Plautus", "Cicero"],
        "correct_answer": "Tacitus"
      },
      {
        "question": "The English words sponsor, spouse, and responsible, as well as the Roman ceremony of Spōnsālia, all derive from the Latin word meaning to",
        "options": ["challenge", "remove", "fear", "promise"],
        "correct_answer": "promise"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which Flavian Emperor ruled for ten years, began building the Colosseum, and was then succeeded by his sons?",
        "options": ["Augustus", "Caligula", "Vespasian", "Hadrian"],
        "correct_answer": "Vespasian"
      },
      {
        "question": "Both Chiron, who was helpful to heroes, and Nessus, who was not, were",
        "options": ["Maenads", "Gorgons", "Satyrs", "Centaurs"],
        "correct_answer": "Centaurs"
      },
      {
        "question": "As Narcissus wasted away, in love with his own reflection, the gods took pity on him and changed him into a",
        "options": ["weeping rock", "flower", "bird", "flowing stream"],
        "correct_answer": "flower"
      },
      {
        "question": "The sentence Cūrā ut valeās! written at the end of a letter is equivalent to the English expression",
        "options": ["Stay well!", "Have fun!", "Be brave!", "Thanks for your help!"],
        "correct_answer": "Stay well!"
      },
      {
        "question": "What Latin motto suggests the difficulty in achieving great things?",
        "options": ["Arma cedant togae", "Ab ovo usque ad mala", "Non est ad astra mollis e terris via", "A mari usque ad mare"],
        "correct_answer": "Non est ad astra mollis e terris via"
      },
      {
        "question": "What official in Rome oversaw games and maintained temples and roads?",
        "options": ["quaestor", "aedile", "consul", "praetor"],
        "correct_answer": "aedile"
      },
      {
        "question": "The line “frangitur inque sinūs scindit sēsē unda reductōs” contains an example of",
        "options": ["alliteration", "anaphora", "polysyndeton", "simile"],
        "correct_answer": "alliteration"
      },
      {
        "question": "What is the metrical pattern of the first four feet of the line “vīderat adductō flectentem cornua nervō”?",
        "options": ["DSSS", "DSSD", "DSDS", "DDSS"],
        "correct_answer": "DSSS"
      },
      {
        "question": "What sponsor of the arts in the Augustan Age was so famous that his name is still used to describe modern patrons?",
        "options": ["Agrippa", "Lucretius", "Maecenas", "Tiberius"],
        "correct_answer": "Maecenas"
      },
      {
        "question": "What Roman poet, author of the Metamorphoses, was exiled by Augustus for “carmen et error”?",
        "options": ["Sulpicia", "Ovid", "Horace", "Catullus"],
        "correct_answer": "Ovid"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which of the following mortal women eventually became immortal?",
        "options": ["Penelope", "Psyche", "Eurydice", "Hecuba"],
        "correct_answer": "Psyche"
      },
      {
        "question": "Aeneas, who was notably devoted to his country, the gods, and his family, is thus especially known for his",
        "options": ["gravitās", "auctōritās", "pietās", "sevēritās"],
        "correct_answer": "pietās"
      },
      {
        "question": "In “…fuit Īlium et ingēns glōria Teucrōrum,” Ilium is another name for",
        "options": ["Pompeii", "Rome", "Sparta", "Troy"],
        "correct_answer": "Troy"
      },
      {
        "question": "What is the name of the 20-book work, of which the 8th book is missing, of stories collected over a winter in Greece?",
        "options": ["Noctes Atticae", "Meditationes", "Hermagoras", "Xenia"],
        "correct_answer": "Noctes Atticae"
      },
      {
        "question": "Of the following, which is the earliest speech of Cicero?",
        "options": ["In Verrem", "In Catilinam", "Pro Quinctio", "Pro Roscio Amerino"],
        "correct_answer": "Pro Quinctio"
      },
      {
        "question": "Name the author of the Xenia who later left Rome and died in Bilbilis, Spain.",
        "options": ["Martial", "Pacuvius", "Persius", "Lucan"],
        "correct_answer": "Martial"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which author was born at modern Padua?",
        "options": ["Pacuvius", "Livy", "Accius", "Tacitus"],
        "correct_answer": "Livy"
      },
      {
        "question": "Ennius skipped over the First Punic War in his Annales as a sign of respect to which author, who had previously written a 7-book work about it?",
        "options": ["Livius Andronicus", "Naevius", "Caecilius Statius", "Lucilius"],
        "correct_answer": "Naevius"
      },
      {
        "question": "Naevius’ Danae and Equus Troianus are examples of what genre?",
        "options": ["Praetextae", "Palliatae", "Cothurnatae", "Riciniatae"],
        "correct_answer": "Cothurnatae"
      },
      {
        "question": "The De Lingua Latina was dedicated to which author?",
        "options": ["Varro Atax", "Cicero", "Varro Reatinus", "Quintilian"],
        "correct_answer": "Varro Reatinus"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which of these works is written in Greek?",
        "options": ["Noctes Atticae", "Hedyphaegetica", "Hebdomades", "Meditationes"],
        "correct_answer": "Meditationes"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which poet was described by Quintilian as “tersus atque elegans”?",
        "options": ["Tibullus", "Propertius", "Horace", "Vergil"],
        "correct_answer": "Tibullus"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which Roman biographer, often of Greeks, also wrote several lost works, including a history of the world in three books?",
        "options": ["Plutarch", "Cornelius Nepos", "Suetonius", "Cornelius Sisenna"],
        "correct_answer": "Cornelius Nepos"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who begins his didactic epic by ironically invoking a goddess, as he states in the work that the gods do not care about human affairs?",
        "options": ["Vergil", "Lucretius", "Ovid", "Caecilius Statius"],
        "correct_answer": "Lucretius"
      },
      {
        "question": "What pupil of Papinian and Praetorian Prefect under Alexander Severus was also a prolific writer of legal works?",
        "options": ["Ulpian", "Gaius", "Julius Solinus", "Aulus Gellius"],
        "correct_answer": "Ulpian"
      },
      {
        "question": "Known as “doctus” because of his work on Hellenic topics, which author also expressed his creativity in painting?",
        "options": ["Ennius", "Naevius", "Pacuvius", "Fabius Iustus"],
        "correct_answer": "Pacuvius"
      },
      {
        "question": "Honorius honored which author with a statue in the Forum of Trajan and by making him the court poet?",
        "options": ["Ausonius", "Prudentius", "Claudian", "Julius Solinus"],
        "correct_answer": "Claudian"
      },
      {
        "question": "Although we hear much about this man, we rarely hear about the fact that he wrote the probable tragedy Prometheus. Who is this?",
        "options": ["Augustus", "Maecenas", "Claudius", "Cicero"],
        "correct_answer": "Claudius"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who served under one of Constantine II’s generals and wrote a 31-book continuation of Tacitus’s histories?",
        "options": ["Aelius Donatus", "Ammianus Marcellinus", "Eutropius", "Trebellius Pollio"],
        "correct_answer": "Ammianus Marcellinus"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who was known as the first “pure” geographer?",
        "options": ["Pliny the Elder", "Columella", "Apicius", "Pomponius Mela"],
        "correct_answer": "Pomponius Mela"
      },
      {
        "question": "“Pingue et floridum” says Macrobius of this orator, whose 10 books of letters were collected by his son.",
        "options": ["Symmachus", "Nonnius Marcellus", "Ambrose", "Vegetius Renatus"],
        "correct_answer": "Symmachus"
      },
      {
        "question": "Leave it to Cicero to be inspirational. Whom did his De Officiis inspire to write a work on the duties of priests?",
        "options": ["Jerome", "Ambrose", "Augustine", "Cyprian"],
        "correct_answer": "Ambrose"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which of the following authors was involved in writing the Historia Augusta from Valerian to Numerian?",
        "options": ["Julius Capitolinus", "Aelius Spartianus", "Aelius Lampridius", "Flavius Vopiscus"],
        "correct_answer": "Flavius Vopiscus"
      },
      {
        "question": "What author of an allegory about the spiritual struggle within the human soul was known as the “Last great Roman poet of the Roman Era”?",
        "options": ["Prudentius", "Lactantius", "Ausonius", "Claudian"],
        "correct_answer": "Prudentius"
      },
      {
        "question": "From what river, in which Midas washed away his golden touch, was Croesus sometimes said to gain his wealth?",
        "options": ["Pactolus", "Iardanus", "Celadon", "Sillas"],
        "correct_answer": "Pactolus"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which of the following does NOT belong in this mythological group?",
        "options": ["Hyperenor", "Udaeus", "Deino", "Pelorus"],
        "correct_answer": "Deino"
      },
      {
        "question": "With whom did Adonis decide to spend his free third of the year?",
        "options": ["Ares", "Apollo", "Artemis", "Aphrodite"],
        "correct_answer": "Aphrodite"
      },
      {
        "question": "On what island was Philoctetes abandoned?",
        "options": ["Delos", "Crete", "Lemnos", "Naxos"],
        "correct_answer": "Lemnos"
      },
      {
        "question": "In the Aeneid, what fury did Juno send to stir up a war in Latium?",
        "options": ["Tisiphone", "Allecto", "Megaera", "Erinyes"],
        "correct_answer": "Allecto"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who was the only person besides Penelope and Odysseus to know the secret of Odysseus’s bed?",
        "options": ["Actoris", "Eurypylus", "Eurycleia", "Eumaeus"],
        "correct_answer": "Eurycleia"
      },
      {
        "question": "By whose fifty daughters did Heracles father fifty children?",
        "options": ["Danaus’", "Erectheus’", "Thespius’", "Minos’"],
        "correct_answer": "Thespius’"
      },
      {
        "question": "What daughter of Eurytus was seduced by Apollo and married Andraemon, who named the god’s son Amphissus?",
        "options": ["Dryope", "Doris", "Eumedes", "Melia"],
        "correct_answer": "Dryope"
      },
      {
        "question": "What son of Oenomaus, follower of Daphne, had his true gender revealed because of Apollo’s jealousy?",
        "options": ["Calisto", "Hymenaios", "Iapyx", "Leucippus"],
        "correct_answer": "Leucippus"
      },
      {
        "question": "With the blood of what animal did Circe purify Jason and Medea?",
        "options": ["cow", "pig", "ram", "dog"],
        "correct_answer": "pig"
      },
      {
        "question": "What legendary poet escaped from pirates to shore by riding on a dolphin?",
        "options": ["Brimo", "Arion", "Idas", "Ischys"],
        "correct_answer": "Arion"
      },
      {
        "question": "Everes and Chariclo were the parents of what seer?",
        "options": ["Tiresias", "Melampus", "Idmon", "Calchas"],
        "correct_answer": "Tiresias"
      },
      {
        "question": "What pious and shape-shifting daughter used her powers to (unsuccessfully) attempt to save her father from his hunger?",
        "options": ["Caenis", "Cornix", "Evadne", "Mestra"],
        "correct_answer": "Mestra"
      },
      {
        "question": "What was the name of the large mechanical siege weapon that hurled rocks?",
        "options": ["ballista", "scorpio", "aries", "onager"],
        "correct_answer": "onager"
      },
      {
        "question": "What month traditionally began the Roman calendar year?",
        "options": ["January", "March", "July", "August"],
        "correct_answer": "March"
      },
      {
        "question": "The small gift baskets containing food presented by patrons to their clients were known as _______.",
        "options": ["dona", "sportula", "salutatio", "clientela"],
        "correct_answer": "sportula"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who in Ancient Rome would most likely be seen wearing a causia, a white hat with a broad rim meant to protect against the sun’s rays?",
        "options": ["freedmen", "aristocrats", "plebeians", "slaves"],
        "correct_answer": "plebeians"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which of the following would have been in charge of the grain supply during the Empire?",
        "options": ["praefectus annonae", "publicanus", "aedile", "censor"],
        "correct_answer": "praefectus annonae"
      },
      {
        "question": "How long was the interregnum between the death of Romulus to the start of Numa Pompilius’ reign?",
        "options": ["Six Months", "One Year", "Two Years", "Seven Years"],
        "correct_answer": "One Year"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which of the following did Servius Tullius NOT establish?",
        "options": ["Temple to Fortuna", "Temple to Diana", "Temple to Jupiter", "Servian Wall"],
        "correct_answer": "Temple to Jupiter"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who was the first magister equitum and three-time consul who proposed the first agrarian law in Rome?",
        "options": ["Titus Lartius", "Publilius Philo", "Spurius Cassius", "Gaius Licinius"],
        "correct_answer": "Spurius Cassius"
      },
      {
        "question": "What consul defeated the pirates at Antium in 338 BC, thus bringing the prows for the rostra to Rome?",
        "options": ["Maenius", "Decius Mus", "Manlius Imperiosus", "Annius"],
        "correct_answer": "Maenius"
      },
      {
        "question": "The folly of Claudius Pulcher led to the victory of the Carthaginians at Drepana under what general?",
        "options": ["Hamilcar", "Hannibal", "Mago", "Adherbal"],
        "correct_answer": "Adherbal"
      },
      {
        "question": "In what year did both Hannibal and Scipio Africanus die?",
        "options": ["201 BC", "195 BC", "191 BC", "183 BC"],
        "correct_answer": "183 BC"
      },
      {
        "question": "Where did Caesar defeat the forces of Pompey led by Metellus Scipio and Juba I?",
        "options": ["Munda", "Thapsus", "Ilerda", "Bagradas Valley"],
        "correct_answer": "Thapsus"
      },
      {
        "question": "What widow of Drusus revealed the treachery of Sejanus to Tiberius?",
        "options": ["Antonia", "Drusilla", "Agrippina", "Julia"],
        "correct_answer": "Antonia"
      },
      {
        "question": "What governor of Lower Germany put down the revolt of Saturninus in 88 AD?",
        "options": ["Ostorius Scapula", "Lappius Maximus", "Flavius Clemens", "Agricola"],
        "correct_answer": "Lappius Maximus"
      },
      {
        "question": "Where did Aurelian defeat Tetricus in 273 AD, thus ending the Gallic Empire?",
        "options": ["Catalaunian Plains", "Emesa", "Immae", "Argentoratum"],
        "correct_answer": "Catalaunian Plains"
      },
      {
        "question": "Who led the Visigoths in a decisive victory over Valens at Adrianople in 378 AD?",
        "options": ["Eugenius", "Arbogast", "Athanaric", "Fritigern"],
        "correct_answer": "Fritigern"
      },
      {
        "question": "What archaeologist excavated the Minoan palace at Knossos?",
        "options": ["Heinrich Schliemann", "Michael Ventris", "Frank Calvert", "Arthur Evans"],
        "correct_answer": "Arthur Evans"
      },
      {
        "question": "The archaeological site at Troy suggests the city was destroyed and rebuilt several times. Which city seems to have been the Troy destroyed by the Trojan War?",
        "options": ["Troy II", "Troy I", "Troy VII", "Troy V"],
        "correct_answer": "Troy VII"
      },
      {
        "question": "What object was discovered by Luigi Pernier in 1908?",
        "options": ["Phaistos Disk", "Arkalochori Axe", "Snake Goddess", "Antikythera Mechanism"],
        "correct_answer": "Phaistos Disk"
      },
      {
        "question": "What is the Greek descriptor for Minoan double-headed axes?",
        "options": ["tholos", "kyklops", "labrys", "kathapsia"],
        "correct_answer": "labrys"
      },
      {
        "question": "The invasion of which people precipitated the fall of the Mycenaean palaces and the rise of the Greek Dark Age?",
        "options": ["Aeolic", "Doric", "Ionic", "Coptic"],
        "correct_answer": "Doric"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the Seven Sages was granted supreme power in Mytilene which he gave up after ten years?",
        "options": ["Cleobulus", "Bias", "Cilon", "Pittacus"],
        "correct_answer": "Pittacus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What tyrant of Mytilene was opposed by the poet Alcaeus?",
        "options": ["Myrsilus", "Melandrus", "Coes", "Lygdamis"],
        "correct_answer": "Myrsilus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the Alcmaeonids cursed his clan by murdering Cylon while he sought refuge on the Acropolis?",
        "options": ["Hippocrates", "Alcmaeon", "Megacles", "Cleisthenes"],
        "correct_answer": "Megacles"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was exiled from Attica in 556 in part for refusing to have a child with Megacles’ daughter?",
        "options": ["Lycurgus", "Peisistratus", "Iophon", "Lygdamis"],
        "correct_answer": "Peisistratus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was responsible for the establishment of the Gerousia?",
        "options": ["Labotas", "Lycurgus", "Aristomenes", "Leon"],
        "correct_answer": "Lycurgus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What war of the seventh century marked the end of Eretria’s and Chalcis’ influence?",
        "options": ["First Sacred", "Second Messinian", "Tegean", "Lelantine"],
        "correct_answer": "Lelantine"
    },
    {
        "question": "What tyrant of Corinth created the diolkos, a method of transporting ships across the Isthmus of Corinth?",
        "options": ["Periander", "Lycophron", "Psammetichus", "Procles"],
        "correct_answer": "Periander"
    },
    {
        "question": "What was the term for Solon’s program of debt relief?",
        "options": ["hektemoroi", "heliaea", "seisachtheia", "zeugita"],
        "correct_answer": "seisachtheia"
    },
    {
        "question": "What city had control of the Olympic Games until 572, when they were taken over by Elis?",
        "options": ["Mycenae", "Argos", "Sparta", "Pisa"],
        "correct_answer": "Pisa"
    },
    {
        "question": "The loss of what island to Athens prompted the decline of Megara?",
        "options": ["Aegina", "Salamis", "Naxos", "Samos"],
        "correct_answer": "Salamis"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whom did the Tyrranicides, Harmodius and Aristogiton, murder in 514?",
        "options": ["Hipparchus", "Peisistratus", "Hippias", "Lygdamis"],
        "correct_answer": "Hipparchus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What Spartan king helped depose the Peisistratids in Athens in 510?",
        "options": ["Anaxandridas", "Leonidas", "Cleomenes", "Cleombrotus"],
        "correct_answer": "Cleomenes"
    },
    {
        "question": "The same Spartan king attempted to aid what opponent of Cleisthenes after the exile of the Peisistratids?",
        "options": ["Megacles", "Aristides", "Isagoras", "Cleon"],
        "correct_answer": "Isagoras"
    },
    {
        "question": "What political party was established by Peisistratus?",
        "options": ["the Plain", "the Hill", "the City", "the Coast"],
        "correct_answer": "the Hill"
    },
    {
        "question": "What city attempted to rebel against Persia in 499, thus sparking the Ionian Revolt?",
        "options": ["Cyme", "Ephesus", "Magnesia", "Miletus"],
        "correct_answer": "Miletus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What tyrant was the leader of the revolt, who incited the Ionian cities after he failed to take the island Naxos?",
        "options": ["Aristagoras", "Eualcides", "Onesilos", "Hecataeus"],
        "correct_answer": "Aristagoras"
    },
    {
        "question": "The destruction of what city in 498 prompted Darius to swear revenge against the Athenians?",
        "options": ["Ephesus", "Miletus", "Lade", "Sardis"],
        "correct_answer": "Sardis"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the runner who told the Athenians about the victory at Battle of Marathon, and then dropped dead of exhaustion?",
        "options": ["Phidias", "Philas", "Pheidippides", "Philoctetes"],
        "correct_answer": "Pheidippides"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the Athenian polemarch who died at the Battle of Marathon?",
        "options": ["Callimachus", "Miltiades", "Cimon", "Aristides"],
        "correct_answer": "Callimachus"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Amphictyonic League and Cleisthenes of Sicyon were allies against Cirrha in what conflict of the 6th century?",
        "options": ["Second Sacred War", "Tegean War", "Lelantine War", "First Sacred War"],
        "correct_answer": "First Sacred War"
    },
    {
        "question": "What strategos was responsible for pushing the Athenians to engage the Persians at Marathon?",
        "options": ["Aristides", "Miltiades", "Simonides", "Stesilaos"],
        "correct_answer": "Miltiades"
    },
    {
        "question": "What god is said to have helped the Athenians at the Battle of Marathon?",
        "options": ["Apollo", "Hermes", "Pan", "Heracles"],
        "correct_answer": "Pan"
    },
    {
        "question": "Miltiades’ unsuccessful attack on what island in 489 prompted his enemies to try him for treason?",
        "options": ["Delos", "Naxos", "Samos", "Paros"],
        "correct_answer": "Naxos"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following was a Persian victory over the Greeks?",
        "options": ["Mycale", "Sestus", "Lade", "Salamis"],
        "correct_answer": "Lade"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the first person recorded as being ostracized in 487?",
        "options": ["Hipparchus", "Megacles", "Xanthippus", "Aristides"],
        "correct_answer": "Hipparchus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What Athenian statesman, who commanded the Athenian contingent at the Battle of Plataea, was known as “the Just”?",
        "options": ["Miltiades", "Aristides", "Callimachus", "Simonides"],
        "correct_answer": "Aristides"
    },
    {
        "question": "What Athenian family supposedly signaled the Persians to attack Athens after Marathon?",
        "options": ["Philaid", "Aeacid", "Alcmaeonid", "Peisistratid"],
        "correct_answer": "Alcmaeonid"
    },
    {
        "question": "What battle took place at the same time as the Battle of Artemisium?",
        "options": ["Plataea", "Mycale", "Himera", "Thermopylae"],
        "correct_answer": "Thermopylae"
    },
    {
        "question": "What Spartan king died at Thermopylae?",
        "options": ["Cleomenes", "Leonidas", "Cleombrotus", "Agis"],
        "correct_answer": "Leonidas"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who benefitted from the Athenian recall of ostracized citizens before the invasion of Xerxes in 480?",
        "options": ["Xanthippus", "Themistocles", "Hipparchus", "Megacles"],
        "correct_answer": "Themistocles"
    },
    {
        "question": "What battle of 478 effectively ended Persian influence in the Hellespont?",
        "options": ["Mycale", "Athos", "Eurymedon", "Sestus"],
        "correct_answer": "Mycale"
    },
    {
        "question": "In what battle did Cimon and the Delian League end Xerxes’ plans for a second invasion of mainland Greece?",
        "options": ["Eurymedon", "Mycale", "Lade", "Athos"],
        "correct_answer": "Eurymedon"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who betrayed the Greeks at Thermopylae by showing the Persians the path around the pass?",
        "options": ["Athenades", "Eurydemus", "Ephialtes", "Phanagoras"],
        "correct_answer": "Ephialtes"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Delian League was formed in 477 as a defensive alliance against whom?",
        "options": ["Sparta", "Persia", "Macedon", "Thebes"],
        "correct_answer": "Persia"
    },
    {
        "question": "Under what syntactic category do words such as fors belong?",
        "options": ["epicene", "monoptote", "diptote", "indeclinable"],
        "correct_answer": "diptote"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these prepositions does NOT take the Ablative?",
        "options": ["coram", "tenus", "absque", "secundum"],
        "correct_answer": "secundum"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following does NOT belong grammatically?",
        "options": ["sodes", "sultis", "sitim", "sitis"],
        "correct_answer": "sitim"
    },
    {
        "question": "What do all of the following have in common grammatically: duplus, triplus, quadruplus?",
        "options": ["They are all multiplicative", "They are all proportional", "They are all distributive", "They are all fractions"],
        "correct_answer": "They are all proportional"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is NOT an island in the bay of Naples?",
        "options": ["Ischia", "Procida", "Pandateria", "Capri"],
        "correct_answer": "Pandateria"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of these cities does NOT border the Pontus Euxinus?",
        "options": ["Cyzicus", "Heraclea", "Sinope", "Trapezus"],
        "correct_answer": "Cyzicus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What river ran through the tribal lands of the Iazyges?",
        "options": ["Porata", "Danuvius", "Tisia", "Tyras"],
        "correct_answer": "Tisia"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which ancient city is located the farthest north?",
        "options": ["Tolosa", "Narbo", "Massilia", "Aquae Sextiae"],
        "correct_answer": "Tolosa"
    },
    {
        "question": "A large island in the eastern Mediterranean, also reputed to be the birthplace of Zeus.",
        "options": ["Sardinia", "Crete", "Sicily", "Cyprus"],
        "correct_answer": "Crete"
    },
    {
        "question": "What building on the Acropolis derives its name from the city’s mythical first king?",
        "options": ["Eleusinium", "Erechtheum", "Propylea", "Pinakotheke"],
        "correct_answer": "Erechtheum"
    },
    {
        "question": "Once a year in September or October, a giant procession began in Athens and walked 25 km northwest up the Sacred Way to which of these cities?",
        "options": ["Thebes", "Delphi", "Olympia", "Eleusis"],
        "correct_answer": "Eleusis"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is not one of the classic seven hills of Rome?",
        "options": ["Vaticanus", "Aventinus", "Palatinus", "Viminalis"],
        "correct_answer": "Vaticanus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which mountain chain is often called the 'backbone of Italy'?",
        "options": ["Alps", "Apennines", "Jura", "Pyrenees"],
        "correct_answer": "Apennines"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following modern day countries was NOT part of Roman Dalmatia?",
        "options": ["Albania", "Croatia", "Romania", "Montenegro"],
        "correct_answer": "Romania"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which river’s water source was the farthest north?",
        "options": ["Tiber", "Bagradas", "Tagus", "Iberus"],
        "correct_answer": "Iberus"
    },
    {
        "question": "According to Caesar, in which province would you have found the following tribes: Ausci, Tarbelli, Sotiates, Volcates, and the Bigerriones?",
        "options": ["Aquitania", "Germania", "Celtica", "Belgica"],
        "correct_answer": "Aquitania"
    },
    {
        "question": "According to Caesar, ubi sunt Ubii?",
        "options": ["in Aquitaniā", "in Germaniā", "in Celticā", "in Belgicā"],
        "correct_answer": "in Germaniā"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following was NOT located on the Palatine Hill?",
        "options": ["Septizodium", "Meta Sudans", "Domus Flavia", "Romulus’ Huts"],
        "correct_answer": "Meta Sudans"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which basilica in the Forum Romanum sat in the northeast near the Velian hill, and was built on the site of Rome’s spice warehouses?",
        "options": ["Maxentius’", "Julian", "Porcia", "Aemiliana"],
        "correct_answer": "Maxentius’"
    },
    {
        "question": "What 3rd principal part means 'I placed'?",
        "options": ["potuī", "pepulī", "posuī", "pandī"],
        "correct_answer": "posuī"
    },
    {
        "question": "What 3rd principal part means 'I lived'?",
        "options": ["vītāvī", "vīcī", "vixī", "vetuī"],
        "correct_answer": "vixī"
    },
    {
        "question": "What 3rd principal part means 'I know'?",
        "options": ["cōgitāvī", "coēgī", "nāvī", "nōvī"],
        "correct_answer": "nōvī"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following verbs means 'to snarl'?",
        "options": ["luctor", "ringor", "stertō", "serpō"],
        "correct_answer": "ringor"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is least like the others?",
        "options": ["scrōfa", "verrēs", "ēricius", "aper"],
        "correct_answer": "ēricius"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is NOT edible?",
        "options": ["furfur", "puls", "bōlētus", "cōs"],
        "correct_answer": "furfur"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is NOT able to fly?",
        "options": ["passer", "pūmiliō", "psittacus", "pāpiliō"],
        "correct_answer": "pūmiliō"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following does NOT refer to a sound?",
        "options": ["tuxtax", "ululō", "hinniō", "glaber"],
        "correct_answer": "glaber"
    },
    {
        "question": "What word does Ovid use to describe the cows who were rivals of Pasiphaë for the love of a bull?",
        "options": ["paelex", "sospes", "laeter", "vidua"],
        "correct_answer": "paelex"
    },
    {
        "question": "What word is used as an exclamation of congratulations?",
        "options": ["vae", "macte", "heu", "apage"],
        "correct_answer": "macte"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which goddess was NOT associated with war?",
        "options": ["Enyo", "Tyche", "Athena", "Bellona"],
        "correct_answer": "Tyche"
    },
    {
        "question": "What seer told Liriope that her newborn son would live a long life 'if he never know himself'?",
        "options": ["Polyeidus", "Mopsus", "Teiresias", "Calchas"],
        "correct_answer": "Teiresias"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the Iliad, who convinces Hypnos to lull Zeus to sleep so that she can aid the Greeks in war?",
        "options": ["Athena", "Iris", "Hera", "Aphrodite"],
        "correct_answer": "Hera"
    },
    {
        "question": "What mountain saved the lives of Deucalion and Pyrrha during the Great Flood?",
        "options": ["Parnassus", "Olympus", "Pelion", "Cithaeron"],
        "correct_answer": "Parnassus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was seduced by Zeus in the form of a flame?",
        "options": ["Persephone", "Europa", "Antiope", "Aegina"],
        "correct_answer": "Aegina"
    },
    {
        "question": "In Book VII of the Aeneid, which Fury takes the form of a priestess of Juno to incite Turnus to fight?",
        "options": ["Tisiphone", "Alecto", "Celaeno", "Megaera"],
        "correct_answer": "Alecto"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following was another name of one of the Hechatonchires?",
        "options": ["Boreas", "Aegaeon", "Grynus", "Cameirus"],
        "correct_answer": "Aegaeon"
    },
    {
        "question": "His name means 'King of the City,' but his father called him by a different name after a local river.",
        "options": ["Bellerophon", "Astyanax", "Paris", "Neoptolemus"],
        "correct_answer": "Astyanax"
    },
    {
        "question": "What region was home to the Lotus-eaters, the Hesperides, and the giant Antaeus?",
        "options": ["Libya", "Mysia", "Thrace", "Thrinacia"],
        "correct_answer": "Libya"
    },
    {
        "question": "What queen of the Phaeacians held significant influence over the decisions of her husband Alcinoüs?",
        "options": ["Nausicaä", "Alcestis", "Arete", "Anticleia"],
        "correct_answer": "Arete"
    },
    {
        "question": "What Thessalian tribe traced their lineage to Apollo and boasted such heroes as Coronus and Caeneus?",
        "options": ["Lapiths", "Myrmidons", "Dorians", "Hellenes"],
        "correct_answer": "Lapiths"
    },
    {
        "question": "He was warned by oracles that his daughter should marry a foreigner and would have handed her over to a Trojan man had his wife not preferred the Rutulian King.",
        "options": ["Cinyras", "Turnus", "Dardanus", "Latinus"],
        "correct_answer": "Latinus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who raped a Hyperborean maiden named Opis and was subsequently shot and killed by Artemis?",
        "options": ["Corythus", "Hippotes", "Tityus", "Orion"],
        "correct_answer": "Orion"
    },
    {
        "question": "The constellation Pisces immortalized the fish that served as the disguises of what two deities as they hid from Typhon?",
        "options": ["Poseidon & Amphitrite", "Zeus & Hera", "Demeter & Persephone", "Aphrodite & Eros"],
        "correct_answer": "Aphrodite & Eros"
    },
    {
        "question": "What son of Nana was so handsome that he was loved by the goddess Cybele?",
        "options": ["Adonis", "Attis", "Androgeus", "Acoetes"],
        "correct_answer": "Attis"
    },
    {
        "question": "What deity had a palace at Aegae?",
        "options": ["Cronus", "Poseidon", "Zeus", "Helius"],
        "correct_answer": "Poseidon"
    },
    {
        "question": "What city was the birthplace and cult center of Asclepius?",
        "options": ["Epidaurus", "Troezen", "Messenia", "Delos"],
        "correct_answer": "Epidaurus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What winged brothers were collectively called the Boreades in reference to their father, the North wind?",
        "options": ["Idas & Lynceus", "Otus & Ephialtes", "Zetes & Calaïs", "Castor & Pollux"],
        "correct_answer": "Zetes & Calaïs"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which was not an offspring of Ge?",
        "options": ["Hemera", "Pontus", "Uranus", "Ourea"],
        "correct_answer": "Hemera"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which deity immortalized the hare as the constellation Lepus?",
        "options": ["Dionysus", "Artemis", "Hera", "Hermes"],
        "correct_answer": "Orion"
    },
    {
        "question": "What man led 80 ships to Troy from the Cretan cities Cnossos, Gortyn, and Phaestus?",
        "options": ["Diomedes", "Sthenelus", "Machaon", "Idomeneus"],
        "correct_answer": "Idomeneus"
    },
    {
        "question": "On what island had Helius pastured his cattle before they were stolen by Alcyoneus?",
        "options": ["Drepane", "Erytheia", "Thrinacia", "Zminthe"],
        "correct_answer": "Erytheia"
    },
    {
        "question": "What group called on nymphs to arbitrate a singing contest between themselves and the Muses?",
        "options": ["Minyades", "Sirens", "Pierides", "Aloadae"],
        "correct_answer": "Pierides"
    },
    {
        "question": "What Arcadian hero, who once sheltered the wounded Iphicles during the war against Augeias, was later shot down by Artemis when he pursued her on Mt. Pholoe?",
        "options": ["Pelasgus", "Apheidas", "Oenopion", "Buphagus"],
        "correct_answer": "Buphagus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What god was celebrated by the people of Asia Minor as a mouse-god named Smintheus?",
        "options": ["Apollo", "Dionysus", "Ares", "Poseidon"],
        "correct_answer": "Apollo"
    },
    {
        "question": "What city in Sicily is considered a possible site of Hades’ abduction of Persephone?",
        "options": ["Henna", "Lilybaeüm", "Camicus", "Eryx"],
        "correct_answer": "Henna"
    },
    {
        "question": "What name did Leucippus adopt when he disguised himself as a girl to get closer to Daphne?",
        "options": ["Ceto", "Oeno", "Manto", "Doso"],
        "correct_answer": "Doso"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which is NOT considered a possible birthplace of Hera?",
        "options": ["Euboea", "Argos", "Eleusis", "Stamphylus"],
        "correct_answer": "Eleusis"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who took command of the Malian contingent sailing to Troy after its leader was abandoned on the coast of Lemnos?",
        "options": ["Leonteus", "Medon", "Peteus", "Eumelus"],
        "correct_answer": "Medon"
    },
    {
        "question": "What king opened up his home in Trachis to the wife and children of Heracles while the hero was travelling?",
        "options": ["Licymnius", "Thespius", "Creon", "Ceyx"],
        "correct_answer": "Creon"
    },
    {
        "question": "In the Odyssey, what son of Euanthes offered Odysseus rare sweet wine in return for his protection?",
        "options": ["Theoclymenus", "Maron", "Telemus", "Ismarus"],
        "correct_answer": "Maron"
    },
    {
        "question": "What child was named for a mark left on his face after it was trampled by a mare?",
        "options": ["Pelias", "Macareus", "Learchus", "Opheltes"],
        "correct_answer": "Opheltes"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who, sometimes listed as a member of the Seven Against Thebes, was said by Homer to have won the contests at Oedipus’ funeral games over all the Thebans?",
        "options": ["Promachus", "Mecisteus", "Parthenopaeüs", "Eteoclus"],
        "correct_answer": "Mecisteus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What king of the Bebryces was killed by Heracles during a war against the Mariandyni?",
        "options": ["Dercynus", "Laogoras", "Mygdon", "Amycus"],
        "correct_answer": "Amycus"
    },
    {
        "question": "I worked so hard on this test that my head was ringing afterwards.",
        "options": ["ut postquam caput meum tintinaret", "ne postquam caput meum tintinavisset", "ut postquam caput meum tintinaverit", "ut postquam caput meum tintinavisset"],
        "correct_answer": "ut postquam caput meum tintinaret"
    },
    {
        "question": "The man said that he had run.",
        "options": ["cucurrisse", "currere", "fore ut cucurrisset", "cursurum esse"],
        "correct_answer": "cucurrisse"
    },
    {
        "question": "The man said that he should have run.",
        "options": ["cucurrisse", "currere", "fore ut cucurrisset", "cursurum esse"],
        "correct_answer": "fore ut cucurrisset"
    },
    {
        "question": "I am sorry for the loss.",
        "options": ["damnum me paenitet.", "damni me paenitet.", "damnum mei paenitet.", "damno mei paenitet."],
        "correct_answer": "damni me paenitet."
    },
    {
        "question": "I am afraid that the news will not be good.",
        "options": ["quin", "ut", "quo", "ne"],
        "correct_answer": "ne"
    },
    {
        "question": "Nolite emere! _______ multo aestimo!",
        "options": ["pluris", "pluro", "pluri", "plus"],
        "correct_answer": "pluris"
    },
    {
        "question": "I have seven horses.",
        "options": ["mihi", "ad me", "me", "meo"],
        "correct_answer": "mihi"
    },
    {
        "question": "The general said that he would have conquered the world, if he had not retired.",
        "options": ["vicisset", "victurum fuisse", "fore ut vicisset", "victurum esset"],
        "correct_answer": "victurum fuisse"
    },
    {
        "question": "I know that the soldier, whom you trusted, is not our enemy.",
        "options": ["credideris", "crederes", "credebas", "credidisti"],
        "correct_answer": "credidisti"
    },
    {
        "question": "Te interrogavi _______ auxilio esset.",
        "options": ["cuius", "cui", "qua", "quem"],
        "correct_answer": "cui"
    },
    {
        "question": "Marcus, pass the torch, please.",
        "options": ["lampades", "lampas", "lampadem", "lampada"],
        "correct_answer": "lampade"
    },
    {
        "question": "The day was so beautiful that we did not go inside.",
        "options": ["ne intro iremus", "ut non intro iremus", "ne intro eamus", "ut non intro eamus"],
        "correct_answer": "ut non intro eamus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Today, the work will be done with great care.",
        "options": ["factum erit", "faciatur", "fiebit", "fiet"],
        "correct_answer": "fiet"
    },
    {
        "question": "There is perhaps nothing better than to love one’s neighbors.",
        "options": ["quo amare", "amandi", "amandis", "amandorum"],
        "correct_answer": "amandis"
    },
    {
        "question": "Marcus was sent in order to carry more tablets.",
        "options": ["Ad portandas", "portatum", "qui portaret", "All of the above"],
        "correct_answer": "All of the above"
    },
    {
        "question": "He taught us many things.",
        "options": ["nos", "nobis", "nostrum", "nostri"],
        "correct_answer": "nobis"
    },
    {
        "question": "Agricola ad agrum _______ ivit.",
        "options": ["frumenta colligenda", "quae frumenta colligeret", "ut frumenta colligat", "frumenta collectum"],
        "correct_answer": "frumenta colligenda"
    },
    {
        "question": "Marcus has kept me here a long time: Iam diu Marcus me _______.",
        "options": ["retinet", "retinebat", "retinuit", "retinuerat"],
        "correct_answer": "retinet"
    },
    {
        "question": "There is no doubt that this Troy would have beaten the Greeks.",
        "options": ["ut", "ne", "quominus", "quin"],
        "correct_answer": "quominus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Si virtutem apud Ciceronem _______, dignus honore sis.",
        "options": ["peteres", "petas", "petis", "petivis"],
        "correct_answer": "petas"
    },
    {
        "question": "Magister est multo sapientior _______.",
        "options": ["quam ego", "me", "mihi", "A and B"],
        "correct_answer": "quam ego"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cicero reum__________ accusavit.",
        "options": ["maiestatem", "maiestatis", "maiestati", "maiestate"],
        "correct_answer": "maiestatis"
    },
    {
        "question": "Est heros _______ di favent.",
        "options": ["quem", "cui", "quo", "cuius"],
        "correct_answer": "cui"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cum lupi _______ non _______, tamen pastor erat maestissimus.",
        "options": ["pecu…nocerent", "pecu…nocuerint", "pecui…nocerent", "pecui…nocuerint"],
        "correct_answer": "pecu…nocerent"
    },
    {
        "question": "Since the toys were not available, the kids played games with sticks and rocks.",
        "options": ["baculla et saxa", "bacullorum et saxorum", "bacullis et saxis", "cum bacullis et saxis"],
        "correct_answer": "cum bacullis et saxis"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cicero coniuratos continue _______ accusat.",
        "options": ["maiestatis", "maiestati", "maiestate", "maiestatem"],
        "correct_answer": "maiestatem"
    },
    {
        "question": "Parentes mel _______ celaverunt.",
        "options": ["a liberis", "liberis", "liberos", "liberorum"],
        "correct_answer": "liberis"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cum parentes mel magna cum cura _______, tamen liberi sumpserunt.",
        "options": ["celabant", "celavissent", "celent", "celaverint"],
        "correct_answer": "celavissent"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cras poeta Ovidius Roma ad insulam _______.",
        "options": ["exsulabitur", "exsulabit", "exsuletur", "exsulat"],
        "correct_answer": "exsulabit"
    },
    {
        "question": "Nisi vero totam orbem _______, sumus indignae _______!",
        "options": ["servemus…honori", "servamus…honori", "servemus…honore", "servamus…honore"],
        "correct_answer": "servemus…honore"
    },
    {
        "question": "_____ petunt quid agam.",
        "options": ["a me", "mihi", "me", "de me"],
        "correct_answer": "a me"
    },
    {
        "question": "There is no one who knows too many things.",
        "options": ["sciverit", "scit", "sciat", "scivit"],
        "correct_answer": "sciat"
    },
    {
        "question": "Supply the verbs needed for a past contrary to fact conditional: Si lupi in media nocte _______, liberi _______.",
        "options": ["ululavissent…territi essent", "ululaverant…territi essent", "ululavissent…territi erant", "ululaverant…territi erant"],
        "correct_answer": "ululavissent…territi essent"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cum pauci eum mirentur, tamen idoneus _______ est.",
        "options": ["ducere", "ducendi", "ducendum", "ducendo"],
        "correct_answer": "ducendo"
    },
    {
        "question": "Quintus, don’t run in the rain!",
        "options": ["noli currere", "ne curras", "cave cucurreris", "All of the above"],
        "correct_answer": "All of the above"
    },
    {
        "question": "Oportet me _______ te bonum ducem.",
        "options": ["vocando", "vocandi", "vocare", "ut vocem"],
        "correct_answer": "vocare"
    },
    {
        "question": "Novem sacerdotes faciem viscerum _______ examinant.",
        "options": ["iecinoris", "iecoris", "iocinoris", "All of the above"],
        "correct_answer": "iecoris"
    },
    {
        "question": "Discipuli discipulaeque summam operam_______ dederunt.",
        "options": ["ad discendam", "discendo", "discendae", "discendum"],
        "correct_answer": "discendum"
    },
    {
        "question": "Cum magna cum diligentia linguam Latinam _______, scivimus nos victuros esse.",
        "options": ["disceremus", "discamus", "didiceramus", "discimus"],
        "correct_answer": "didiceramus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Marcus ad forum _____ ut equum vendat.",
        "options": ["it", "ivit", "ibat", "iret"],
        "correct_answer": "ivit"
    },
    {
        "question": "We will not tolerate such foul speech!",
        "options": ["taeteram linguam", "taetram linguam", "taeterae linguae", "taetrae lingua"],
        "correct_answer": "taetram linguam"
    },
    {
        "question": "Unfortunately, the students only completed two thirds of their homework.",
        "options": ["bis tertiam partem", "duae tertiae", "duas partes", "B and C"],
        "correct_answer": "B and C"
    },
    {
        "question": "The soldiers will return within a few hours.",
        "options": ["paucis horis", "paucas horas", "in paucis horis", "intra paucas horas"],
        "correct_answer": "in paucis horis"
    },
    {
        "question": "Caesar’s assassination was no more tragic than if he had lived!",
        "options": ["quasi", "tamquam si", "quam si", "ceu"],
        "correct_answer": "tamquam si"
    },
    {
        "question": "Our friends acted bravely because of love for us.",
        "options": ["amori nostri", "amori nostrum", "amore nostri", "amore nostrum"],
        "correct_answer": "amore nostrum"
    },
    {
        "question": "Eheu, _______ Romae non _______!",
        "options": ["te…es", "tu…futurum esse", "te…futurum esse", "B and C"],
        "correct_answer": "B and C"
    },
    {
        "question": "She was born on July 18th.",
        "options": ["quarto die post Idus Iulias", "a. d. xv. Kal. Sext.", "tertio die post Idus Iulias", "a. d. xvi. Kal Sext."],
        "correct_answer": "a. d. xv. Kal. Sext."
    },
    {
        "question": "Young ones, when at first you don’t succeed, try again!",
        "options": ["conate", "conare", "conari", "conamini"],
        "correct_answer": "conamini"
    },
    {
        "question": "If he notices that I took the whole cake, he will be very sad.",
        "options": ["animadverterit…erit", "animadverterit…fuerit", "animadvertat…sit", "animadvertit…erit"],
        "correct_answer": "animadverterit…erit"
    },
    {
        "question": "After the enemies were defeated, Pompey returned to Rome.",
        "options": ["Post hostes victi sint", "hostibus victis", "Post hostes victi esset", "hostes victos"],
        "correct_answer": "hostibus victis"
    },
    {
        "question": "Marius _______ natus est.",
        "options": ["gentem notam", "genti notae", "gente nota", "gentis notae"],
        "correct_answer": "gentis notae"
    },
    {
        "question": "The professor asks her students what they will do after graduation.",
        "options": ["facient", "facturi sint", "fecerint", "Not Possible"],
        "correct_answer": "facturi sint"
    },
    {
        "question": "That incident was most terrible to see!",
        "options": ["terribillimum visum", "terribillimum visu", "terribilissimum visum", "terribilissimum visu"],
        "correct_answer": "terribilissimum visum"
    },
    {
        "question": "These mountains were an impediment to the army.",
        "options": ["impedimento exercitui", "impedimentum exercitus", "impedimentum ad exercitum", "impedimento ad exercitum"],
        "correct_answer": "impedimento exercitui"
    },
    {
        "question": "We snuck through the kitchen as quickly as possible.",
        "options": ["celerrime", "quam celerrime", "quam celerius", "celerius"],
        "correct_answer": "quam celerrime"
    },
    {
        "question": "Would that I had not wasted all of that time!",
        "options": ["utinam", "dudum", "quin", "vae"],
        "correct_answer": "utinam"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is Livius Andronicus' full name?",
      "options": ["Marcus Livius Andronicus", "Lucius Livius Andronicus", "Gaius Livius Andronicus", "Publius Livius Andronicus"],
      "correct_answer": "Lucius Livius Andronicus"
    },
    {
      "question": "What author was born in 284 B.C. at Tarentum?",
      "options": ["Ennius", "Plautus", "Livius Andronicus", "Terence"],
      "correct_answer": "Livius Andronicus"
    },
    {
      "question": "Where was Livius Andronicus born in 284 B.C.?",
      "options": ["Rome", "Naples", "Capua", "Tarentum"],
      "correct_answer": "Tarentum"
    },
    {
      "question": "In what year was Livius Andronicus born at Tarentum?",
      "options": ["264 BC", "284 BC", "304 BC", "324 BC"],
      "correct_answer": "284 BC"
    },
    {
      "question": "In what year did Livius Andronicus die?",
      "options": ["204 BC", "224 BC", "244 BC", "264 BC"],
      "correct_answer": "204 BC"
    },
    {
      "question": "What author was called the 'Father of Latin Literature'?",
      "options": ["Ennius", "Plautus", "Livius Andronicus", "Terence"],
      "correct_answer": "Livius Andronicus"
    },
    {
      "question": "What honorific title was given to Livius Andronicus?",
      "options": ["Father of Latin Poetry", "Father of Latin Drama", "Father of Latin Epics", "Father of Latin Literature"],
      "correct_answer": "Father of Latin Literature"
    },
    {
      "question": "In what year did Livius Andronicus come to Rome as a slave?",
      "options": ["292 BC", "282 BC", "272 BC", "262 BC"],
      "correct_answer": "272 BC"
    },
    {
      "question": "What author came to Rome as a slave in 272 BC?",
      "options": ["Ennius", "Plautus", "Livius Andronicus", "Terence"],
      "correct_answer": "Livius Andronicus"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which work of Livius Andronicus is a Latin translation of Homer's Odyssey?",
      "options": ["Aeneid", "Odyssey", "Odussia", "Metamorphoses"],
      "correct_answer": "Odussia"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who wrote the first Latin translation of Homer's Odyssey?",
      "options": ["Ennius", "Plautus", "Livius Andronicus", "Terence"],
      "correct_answer": "Livius Andronicus"
    },
    {
      "question": "What was the earliest extant work of Latin literature?",
      "options": ["Aeneid", "Metamorphoses", "Odussia", "Georgics"],
      "correct_answer": "Odussia"
    },
    {
      "question": "What was the purpose of Livius Andronicus' Odussia?",
      "options": ["entertainment", "propaganda", "textbook", "religious"],
      "correct_answer": "textbook"
    },
    {
      "question": "For whose children did Livius Andronicus compose the Odussia as a textbook?",
      "options": ["Scipio Africanus", "Livius Salinator", "Marcus Aurelius", "Julius Caesar"],
      "correct_answer": "Livius Salinator"
    },
    {
      "question": "In what early Italian meter was the Odussia written?",
      "options": ["Dactylic Hexameter", "Elegiac Couplets", "Iambic Trimeter", "Saturnian"],
      "correct_answer": "Saturnian"
    },
    {
      "question": "What Latin term did Livius Andronicus use to translate 'Muse'?",
      "options": ["Camena", "Nympha", "Dea", "Nymphae"],
      "correct_answer": "Camena"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who wrote the first Roman comedy and Roman tragedy for the Ludi Romani of 240 BC?",
      "options": ["Plautus", "Terence", "Livius Andronicus", "Ennius"],
      "correct_answer": "Livius Andronicus"
    },
    {
      "question": "For what event in 240 BC did Livius Andronicus compose the first Roman comedy and tragedy?",
      "options": ["Ludi Plebeii", "Ludi Romani", "Saturnalia", "Floralia"],
      "correct_answer": "Ludi Romani"
    },
    {
      "question": "What author was the first to produce plays in Rome?",
      "options": ["Plautus", "Terence", "Livius Andronicus", "Ennius"],
      "correct_answer": "Livius Andronicus"
    },
    {
      "question": "What author composed a parthenion in honor of Juno in 207 BC?",
      "options": ["Plautus", "Terence", "Livius Andronicus", "Ennius"],
      "correct_answer": "Livius Andronicus"
    },
    {
      "question": "What type of poem did Livius Andronicus compose in honor of Juno in 207 BC?",
      "options": ["epic", "elegy", "parthenion", "ode"],
      "correct_answer": "parthenion"
    },
    {
      "question": "In what year did Livius Andronicus compose a parthenion in honor of Juno?",
      "options": ["207 BC", "217 BC", "227 BC", "237 BC"],
      "correct_answer": "207 BC"
    },
    {
      "question": "What author regarded Livius Andronicus' work as antiquated and not worth reading?",
      "options": ["Cato", "Varro", "Cicero", "Seneca"],
      "correct_answer": "Cicero"
    },
    {
      "question": "What author was born in 270 BC at Capua?",
      "options": ["Plautus", "Terence", "Gnaeus Naevius", "Ennius"],
      "correct_answer": "Gnaeus Naevius"
    },
    {
      "question": "In what year was Gnaeus Naevius born near Capua?",
      "options": ["280 BC", "270 BC", "260 BC", "250 BC"],
      "correct_answer": "270 BC"
    },
    {
      "question": "Where did Gnaeus Naevius die in exile in 201 BC?",
      "options": ["Carthage", "Syracuse", "Rome", "Utica"],
      "correct_answer": "Utica"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which author died at Utica in 201 BC?",
      "options": ["Plautus", "Terence", "Gnaeus Naevius", "Ennius"],
      "correct_answer": "Gnaeus Naevius"
    },
    {
      "question": "In what year did Gnaeus Naevius die in exile at Utica?",
      "options": ["201 BC", "211 BC", "221 BC", "231 BC"],
      "correct_answer": "201 BC"
    },
    {
      "question": "What dramatist was the first native Italian to write Latin literature?",
      "options": ["Plautus", "Terence", "Gnaeus Naevius", "Ennius"],
      "correct_answer": "Gnaeus Naevius"
    },
    {
      "question": "What author pioneered 'fabulae praetextae', tragedies written on Roman historical material?",
      "options": ["Plautus", "Terence", "Gnaeus Naevius", "Ennius"],
      "correct_answer": "Gnaeus Naevius"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are fabulae praetextae?",
      "options": ["comedies on Roman themes", "historical narratives", "tragedies written on Roman historical material", "epic poems"],
      "correct_answer": "tragedies written on Roman historical material"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who was the first to write an epic on an entirely Italian subject?",
      "options": ["Plautus", "Terence", "Gnaeus Naevius", "Ennius"],
      "correct_answer": "Gnaeus Naevius"
    },
    {
      "question": "What was the title of Naevius' epic on the First Punic War?",
      "options": ["Aeneid", "Iliad", "Bellum Punicum", "Metamorphoses"],
      "correct_answer": "Bellum Punicum"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who wrote the Bellum Punicum, the first epic on an Italian subject?",
      "options": ["Plautus", "Terence", "Gnaeus Naevius", "Ennius"],
      "correct_answer": "Gnaeus Naevius"
    },
    {
      "question": "To what African city was Naevius exiled because of his feud with the Metelli family?",
      "options": ["Carthage", "Syracuse", "Rome", "Utica"],
      "correct_answer": "Utica"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which author was exiled to Utica because of his feud with the Metelli family?",
      "options": ["Plautus", "Terence", "Gnaeus Naevius", "Ennius"],
      "correct_answer": "Gnaeus Naevius"
    },
    {
      "question": "With what family did Gnaeus Naevius have a feud which got him exiled to Utica?",
      "options": ["Cornelii", "Fabii", "Metelli", "Claudians"],
      "correct_answer": "Metelli"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which author remarked 'Fato Metelli fiunt Romae consules'?",
      "options": ["Plautus", "Terence", "Gnaeus Naevius", "Ennius"],
      "correct_answer": "Gnaeus Naevius"
    },
    {
      "question": "Translate Naevius' remark 'fato Metelli fiunt Romae consules'.",
      "options": ["By fate the Metelli become consuls at Rome", "By fate the Metelli rule Rome", "By fate the Metelli lead Rome", "By fate the Metelli govern Rome"],
      "correct_answer": "It's fate that makes the Metelli consuls at Rome"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which work of Gnaeus Naevius is an epic poem about the First Punic War, written in Saturnian verse?",
      "options": ["Aeneid", "Iliad", "Bellum Punicum", "Metamorphoses"],
      "correct_answer": "Bellum Punicum"
    },
    {
      "question": "Whose Bellum Punicum details the events from Aeneas' arrival in Latium down to the First Punic War?",
      "options": ["Plautus", "Terence", "Gnaeus Naevius", "Ennius"],
      "correct_answer": "Gnaeus Naevius"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many books did Naevius' Bellum Punicum contain?",
      "options": ["5", "6", "7", "8"],
      "correct_answer": "7"
    },
    {
      "question": "What grammarian arranged Naevius' Bellum Punicum into 7 Books?",
      "options": ["Varro", "Donatus", "Lampadio", "Servius"],
      "correct_answer": "Lampadio"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are the titles of Naevius' two fabulae praetextae?",
      "options": ["Amphitryon & Miles Gloriosus", "Menaechmi & Pseudolus", "Clastidium & Romulus", "Rudens & Curculio"],
      "correct_answer": "Clastidium & Romulus"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who wrote a fabula praetexta entitled Clastidium?",
      "options": ["Plautus", "Terence", "Gnaeus Naevius", "Ennius"],
      "correct_answer": "Gnaeus Naevius"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who wrote a fabula praetexta entitled Romulus?",
      "options": ["Plautus", "Terence", "Gnaeus Naevius", "Ennius"],
      "correct_answer": "Gnaeus Naevius"
    },
    {
      "question": "What was Plautus' full name?",
      "options": ["Titus Maccius Plautus", "Marcus Plautus", "Gaius Plautus", "Lucius Plautus"],
      "correct_answer": "Titus Maccius Plautus"
    },
    {
      "question": "Where was Plautus born c. 254 BC?",
      "options": ["Rome", "Naples", "Sarsina", "Capua"],
      "correct_answer": "Sarsina"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which author was born at Sarsina c. 254 BC?",
      "options": ["Terence", "Ennius", "Plautus", "Livius Andronicus"],
      "correct_answer": "Plautus"
    },
    {
      "question": "In what year did Plautus die?",
      "options": ["204 BC", "184 BC", "164 BC", "144 BC"],
      "correct_answer": "184 BC"
    },
    {
      "question": "What comic playwright was born at Sarsina c. 254 BC?",
      "options": ["Terence", "Ennius", "Plautus", "Livius Andronicus"],
      "correct_answer": "Plautus"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which Broadway play is based on a compilation of Plautus' plays?",
      "options": ["West Side Story", "A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum", "Cats", "Les Misérables"],
      "correct_answer": "A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Broadway play 'A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum' is based on a compilation of which author's plays?",
      "options": ["Terence", "Ennius", "Plautus", "Livius Andronicus"],
      "correct_answer": "Plautus"
    },
    {
      "question": "Varro said that if the Muses had spoken Latin they would have spoken the type that appeared in which author's plays?",
      "options": ["Terence", "Ennius", "Plautus", "Livius Andronicus"],
      "correct_answer": "Plautus"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which play of Plautus deals with a clever slave who manages to steal away from the boastful soldier Pyrgopolyneices the girl loved by his young master?",
      "options": ["Mostellaria", "Miles Gloriosus", "Aulularia", "Pseudolus"],
      "correct_answer": "Miles Gloriosus"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the translation of 'Miles Gloriosus'?",
      "options": ["The Haunted House", "The Pot of Gold", "The Braggart Soldier", "The Twin Brothers"],
      "correct_answer": "The Braggart Soldier"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which play of Plautus was his longest?",
      "options": ["Mostellaria", "Miles Gloriosus", "Aulularia", "Pseudolus"],
      "correct_answer": "Miles Gloriosus"
    },
    {
      "question": "In Plautus' Miles Gloriosus, what boastful soldier is swindled out of his girl?",
      "options": ["Tranio", "Pyrgopolyneices", "Ballio", "Euclio"],
      "correct_answer": "Pyrgopolyneices"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which play of Plautus deals with the slave Tranio who convinces his master's father that his house is haunted?",
      "options": ["Mostellaria", "Miles Gloriosus", "Aulularia", "Pseudolus"],
      "correct_answer": "Mostellaria"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the translation of 'Mostellaria'?",
      "options": ["The Braggart Soldier", "The Pot of Gold", "The Haunted House", "The Twin Brothers"],
      "correct_answer": "The Haunted House"
    },
    {
      "question": "In Plautus' Mostellaria, what clever slave convinces his master's father that his house is haunted?",
      "options": ["Pyrgopolyneices", "Tranio", "Ballio", "Euclio"],
      "correct_answer": "Tranio"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which play of Plautus deals with the misfortunes of a miser named Euclio who tries to hide his fortune?",
      "options": ["Mostellaria", "Miles Gloriosus", "Aulularia", "Pseudolus"],
      "correct_answer": "Aulularia"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the translation of 'Aulularia'?",
      "options": ["The Braggart Soldier", "The Pot of Gold", "The Haunted House", "The Twin Brothers"],
      "correct_answer": "The Pot of Gold"
    },
    {
      "question": "In Plautus' Aulularia, what miser tries to hide his fortune?",
      "options": ["Pyrgopolyneices", "Tranio", "Ballio", "Euclio"],
      "correct_answer": "Euclio"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which play of Plautus deals with a clever slave who tricks the pimp Ballio out of a girl his young master loves?",
      "options": ["Mostellaria", "Miles Gloriosus", "Aulularia", "Pseudolus"],
      "correct_answer": "Pseudolus"
    },
    {
      "question": "In Plautus' Pseudolus, what pimp is swindled out of one of his girls?",
      "options": ["Pyrgopolyneices", "Tranio", "Ballio", "Euclio"],
      "correct_answer": "Ballio"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which play of Plautus deals with twins separated at birth?",
      "options": ["Mostellaria", "Miles Gloriosus", "Menaechmi", "Pseudolus"],
      "correct_answer": "Menaechmi"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which play of Plautus is the primary model for Shakespeare's Comedy of Errors?",
      "options": ["Mostellaria", "Miles Gloriosus", "Menaechmi", "Pseudolus"],
      "correct_answer": "Menaechmi"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which play of Plautus deals with the confusion over Hercules' birth?",
      "options": ["Amphitruo", "Miles Gloriosus", "Menaechmi", "Pseudolus"],
      "correct_answer": "Amphitruo"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which play of Plautus is the only one with a mythological subject?",
      "options": ["Amphitruo", "Miles Gloriosus", "Menaechmi", "Pseudolus"],
      "correct_answer": "Amphitruo"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which play of Plautus deals with the efforts of a well-to-do father to ransom his son who has been taken prisoner of war?",
      "options": ["Amphitruo", "Miles Gloriosus", "Captivi", "Pseudolus"],
      "correct_answer": "Captivi"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which play of Plautus mentions the imprisonment of Naevius?",
      "options": ["Amphitruo", "Miles Gloriosus", "Captivi", "Pseudolus"],
      "correct_answer": "Captivi"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which play of Plautus has no female characters?",
      "options": ["Amphitruo", "Miles Gloriosus", "Captivi", "Pseudolus"],
      "correct_answer": "Captivi"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which play of Plautus deals with a parasite of a young man who is in love with a courtesan?",
      "options": ["Curculio", "Miles Gloriosus", "Captivi", "Pseudolus"],
      "correct_answer": "Curculio"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which play of Plautus was his shortest?",
      "options": ["Curculio", "Miles Gloriosus", "Captivi", "Pseudolus"],
      "correct_answer": "Curculio"
    },
    {
      "question": "What author was born in 239 BC at Rudiae in Calabria?",
      "options": ["Quintus Ennius", "Gnaeus Naevius", "Marcus Pacuvius", "Titus Maccius Plautus"],
      "correct_answer": "Quintus Ennius"
    },
    {
      "question": "Where was Quintus Ennius born in 239 BC?",
      "options": ["Rudiae (in Calabria)", "Rome", "Capua", "Sarsina"],
      "correct_answer": "Rudiae (in Calabria)"
    },
    {
      "question": "In what year did Quintus Ennius die?",
      "options": ["169 BC", "204 BC", "184 BC", "130 BC"],
      "correct_answer": "169 BC"
    },
    {
      "question": "What author wrote an 18-book epic on Roman history entitled Annales?",
      "options": ["Quintus Ennius", "Livius Andronicus", "Plautus", "Cato the Elder"],
      "correct_answer": "Quintus Ennius"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many books did Ennius' Annales contain?",
      "options": ["18", "7", "12", "24"],
      "correct_answer": "18"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which work of Quintus Ennius is an 18-book epic poem on Roman history?",
      "options": ["Annales", "Odussia", "Bellum Punicum", "Origines"],
      "correct_answer": "Annales"
    },
    {
      "question": "What author first adapted dactylic hexameter from Greek poetry into Latin?",
      "options": ["Quintus Ennius", "Homer", "Virgil", "Ovid"],
      "correct_answer": "Quintus Ennius"
    },
    {
      "question": "What author made dactylic hexameter the official meter of Latin epic poetry?",
      "options": ["Quintus Ennius", "Ovid", "Virgil", "Livius Andronicus"],
      "correct_answer": "Quintus Ennius"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who brought Quintus Ennius to Rome?",
      "options": ["Cato the Elder", "Scipio Africanus", "Cicero", "Livius Andronicus"],
      "correct_answer": "Cato the Elder"
    },
    {
      "question": "What poet claimed that he had three hearts because he spoke Latin, Greek, and Oscan?",
      "options": ["Quintus Ennius", "Cicero", "Homer", "Livius Andronicus"],
      "correct_answer": "Quintus Ennius"
    },
    {
      "question": "What three languages made up Ennius' three hearts?",
      "options": ["Greek, Oscan, Latin", "Latin, Etruscan, Greek", "Latin, Greek, Phoenician", "Oscan, Etruscan, Latin"],
      "correct_answer": "Greek, Oscan, Latin"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who was the first Latin writer to compose Satire?",
      "options": ["Quintus Ennius", "Horace", "Juvenal", "Persius"],
      "correct_answer": "Quintus Ennius"
    },
    {
      "question": "What nephew of Ennius was a famous tragedian?",
      "options": ["Pacuvius", "Naevius", "Plautus", "Terence"],
      "correct_answer": "Pacuvius"
    },
    {
      "question": "What poet was the famous uncle of Pacuvius?",
      "options": ["Quintus Ennius", "Homer", "Virgil", "Cicero"],
      "correct_answer": "Quintus Ennius"
    },
    {
      "question": "What was Pacuvius' full name?",
      "options": ["Marcus Pacuvius", "Gaius Pacuvius", "Quintus Pacuvius", "Lucius Pacuvius"],
      "correct_answer": "Marcus Pacuvius"
    },
    {
      "question": "Where was Pacuvius in 220 BC?",
      "options": ["Brundisium", "Rome", "Capua", "Sarsina"],
      "correct_answer": "Brundisium"
    },
    {
      "question": "In what year was Pacuvius born in Brundisium?",
      "options": ["220 BC", "234 BC", "239 BC", "270 BC"],
      "correct_answer": "220 BC"
    },
    {
      "question": "In what year did Pacuvius die?",
      "options": ["130 BC", "169 BC", "204 BC", "184 BC"],
      "correct_answer": "130 BC"
    },
    {
      "question": "What author did Cicero consider the \"greatest of Latin tragic poets\"?",
      "options": ["Pacuvius", "Naevius", "Plautus", "Quintus Ennius"],
      "correct_answer": "Pacuvius"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who considered Pacuvius the greatest of Latin tragic poets?",
      "options": ["Cicero", "Virgil", "Horace", "Ovid"],
      "correct_answer": "Cicero"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which work of Pacuvius depicts Orestes driven mad by the Furies?",
      "options": ["Dulorestes", "Niptra", "Medea", "Pseudolus"],
      "correct_answer": "Dulorestes"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the translation of Dulorestes?",
      "options": ["Orestes the Slave", "Orestes the King", "Orestes the Hero", "Orestes the Madman"],
      "correct_answer": "Orestes the Slave"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who wrote the tragedies Dulorestes and Niptra?",
      "options": ["Pacuvius", "Plautus", "Naevius", "Terence"],
      "correct_answer": "Pacuvius"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which work of Pacuvius depicts Ulysses' death at the hands of Telegonus?",
      "options": ["Niptra", "Dulorestes", "Hecuba", "Ajax"],
      "correct_answer": "Niptra"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the translation of Niptra?",
      "options": ["The Bath", "The Shipwreck", "The Return", "The Quest"],
      "correct_answer": "The Bath"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is Cato the Elder's full name?",
      "options": ["Marcus Porcius Cato", "Gaius Julius Caesar", "Lucius Cornelius Sulla", "Gnaeus Pompeius Magnus"],
      "correct_answer": "Marcus Porcius Cato"
    },
    {
      "question": "What author was born in 234 BC at Tusculum?",
      "options": ["Cato the Elder", "Plautus", "Ennius", "Naevius"],
      "correct_answer": "Cato the Elder"
    },
    {
      "question": "Where was Cato the Elder born in 234 BC?",
      "options": ["Tusculum", "Rome", "Brundisium", "Capua"],
      "correct_answer": "Tusculum"
    },
    {
      "question": "In what year was Cato the Elder born at Tusculum?",
      "options": ["234 BC", "270 BC", "239 BC", "220 BC"],
      "correct_answer": "234 BC"
    },
    {
      "question": "In what year did Cato the Elder die?",
      "options": ["149 BC", "130 BC", "169 BC", "184 BC"],
      "correct_answer": "149 BC"
    },
    {
      "question": "What author was called the \"Father of Latin Prose\"?",
      "options": ["Cato the Elder", "Cicero", "Plautus", "Quintus Ennius"],
      "correct_answer": "Cato the Elder"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who was the first to write history in Latin?",
      "options": ["Cato the Elder", "Livius Andronicus", "Quintus Ennius", "Plautus"],
      "correct_answer": "Cato the Elder"
    },
    {
      "question": "What author brought Quintius Ennius to Rome?",
      "options": ["Cato the Elder", "Scipio Africanus", "Cicero", "Plautus"],
      "correct_answer": "Cato the Elder"
    },
    {
      "question": "What political office did Cato the Elder hold in 184 BC?",
      "options": ["censor", "consul", "praetor", "aedile"],
      "correct_answer": "censor"
    },
    {
      "question": "What author, known for his old-fashioned and puritanical style, was called the \"father of Latin prose\"?",
      "options": ["Cato the Elder", "Cicero", "Virgil", "Quintus Ennius"],
      "correct_answer": "Cato the Elder"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which work of Cato the Elder was a 7-book history of Rome?",
      "options": ["Origines", "De Agri Cultura", "De Re Rustica", "De Bello Gallico"],
      "correct_answer": "Origines"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many books did Cato's Origines contain?",
      "options": ["7", "10", "12", "5"],
      "correct_answer": "7"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which work of Cato the Elder begins with a line of hexameter?",
      "options": ["Origines", "De Agri Cultura", "De Bello Gallico", "De Re Rustica"],
      "correct_answer": "Origines"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which work of Cato the Elder was the first prose historical text in Latin?",
      "options": ["Origines", "De Agri Cultura", "De Bello Gallico", "De Re Rustica"],
      "correct_answer": "Origines"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which work of Cato the Elder was a treatise on farming?",
      "options": ["De Agri Cultura", "Origines", "De Bello Gallico", "De Re Rustica"],
      "correct_answer": "De Agri Cultura"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the alternate title of Cato's De Agri Cultura?",
      "options": ["De Re Rustica", "De Bello Gallico", "Origines", "De Agri Cultura"],
      "correct_answer": "De Re Rustica"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which work of Cato the Elder was the earliest Latin prose work to come down to us in its entirety?",
      "options": ["De Agri Cultura", "Origines", "De Bello Gallico", "De Re Rustica"],
      "correct_answer": "De Agri Cultura"
    },
    {
      "question": "What was Terence's full name?",
      "options": ["Publius Terentius Afer", "Marcus Terentius Varro", "Gaius Terentius Hortalus", "Lucius Terentius Aristophanes"],
      "correct_answer": "Publius Terentius Afer"
    },
    {
      "question": "What author was born ca. 195 BC in Carthage?",
      "options": ["Terence", "Plautus", "Naevius", "Ennius"],
      "correct_answer": "Terence"
    },
    {
      "question": "Where was Terence born in 195 or 185 BC?",
      "options": ["Carthage", "Rome", "Sarsina", "Brundisium"],
      "correct_answer": "Carthage"
    },
    {
      "question": "In what year did Terence die?",
      "options": ["159 BC", "174 BC", "166 BC", "130 BC"],
      "correct_answer": "159 BC"
    },
    {
      "question": "What comic playwright was born in Carthage in 195 BC?",
      "options": ["Terence", "Plautus", "Naevius", "Ennius"],
      "correct_answer": "Terence"
    },
    {
      "question": "What style of Greek comedy did Plautus and Terence employ?",
      "options": ["New Comedy", "Old Comedy", "Satyr Play", "Tragedy"],
      "correct_answer": "New Comedy"
    },
    {
      "question": "What comic playwright was brought to Rome from Carthage as a slave?",
      "options": ["Terence", "Plautus", "Naevius", "Ennius"],
      "correct_answer": "Terence"
    },
    {
      "question": "In what year did Terence make his theatrical debut?",
      "options": ["166 BC", "159 BC", "174 BC", "180 BC"],
      "correct_answer": "166 BC"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who was the literary patron of Terence?",
      "options": ["Scipio Aemilianus", "Cato the Elder", "Julius Caesar", "Pompey the Great"],
      "correct_answer": "Scipio Aemilianus"
    },
    {
      "question": "In what city were all of Terence's plays set?",
      "options": ["Athens", "Rome", "Syracuse", "Sparta"],
      "correct_answer": "Athens"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who acted in all of Terence's plays?",
      "options": ["Ambivius Turpio", "Roscius", "Cicero", "Plautus"],
      "correct_answer": "Ambivius Turpio"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which play of Terence was his earliest work?",
      "options": ["Andria", "Eunuchus", "Adelphi", "Heauton Timorumenos"],
      "correct_answer": "Andria"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the translation of 'Andria'?",
      "options": ["The Woman of Andros", "The Man of Andros", "The Woman of Athens", "The Man of Athens"],
      "correct_answer": "The Woman of Andros"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the prologue of which of Terence's plays does he defend his use of contaminatio?",
      "options": ["Andria", "Eunuchus", "Adelphi", "Heauton Timorumenos"],
      "correct_answer": "Andria"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is contaminatio?",
      "options": ["Combination of elements of multiple Greek plays into one Latin play", "A type of Greek tragedy", "A Roman comedic dance", "A form of Latin poetry"],
      "correct_answer": "Combination of elements of multiple Greek plays into one Latin play"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the translation of 'Adelphi'?",
      "options": ["The Brothers", "The Sisters", "The Parents", "The Cousins"],
      "correct_answer": "The Brothers"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which play of Terence is a comedy about twins, one born in the country and one born in the city?",
      "options": ["Adelphi", "Eunuchus", "Hecyra", "Heauton Timorumenos"],
      "correct_answer": "Adelphi"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which play of Terence was his biggest commercial success?",
      "options": ["Eunuchus", "Andria", "Hecyra", "Adelphi"],
      "correct_answer": "Eunuchus"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the translation of 'Hecyra'?",
      "options": ["The Mother-in-Law", "The Wife", "The Aunt", "The Daughter"],
      "correct_answer": "The Mother-in-Law"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which play of Terence was only produced after two failed attempts?",
      "options": ["Hecyra", "Eunuchus", "Adelphi", "Andria"],
      "correct_answer": "Hecyra"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which play of Terence did the audience leave in preference for a show of tightrope walkers during the first and second attempts?",
      "options": ["Hecyra", "Eunuchus", "Andria", "Adelphi"],
      "correct_answer": "Hecyra"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the translation of 'Heauton Timorumenos'?",
      "options": ["The Self-Tormentor", "The Self-Punisher", "The Self-Defender", "The Self-Critic"],
      "correct_answer": "The Self-Tormentor"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which play of Terence deals with Clinia who is about to be separated from his wife?",
      "options": ["Heauton Timorumenos", "Eunuchus", "Hecyra", "Adelphi"],
      "correct_answer": "Heauton Timorumenos"
    },
    {
      "question": "In which play of Terence does the title character remark 'homo sum, humani nil a me alienum puto'?",
      "options": ["Heauton Timorumenos", "Andria", "Eunuchus", "Adelphi"],
      "correct_answer": "Heauton Timorumenos"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is Lucilius' full name?",
      "options": ["Gaius Lucilius", "Publius Lucilius", "Marcus Lucilius", "Titus Lucilius"],
      "correct_answer": "Gaius Lucilius"
    },
    {
      "question": "In what year was Lucilius born?",
      "options": ["180 BC", "160 BC", "150 BC", "200 BC"],
      "correct_answer": "180 BC"
    },
    {
      "question": "Where was Lucilius born in 180 BC?",
      "options": ["Suessa Aurunca", "Rome", "Capua", "Brundisium"],
      "correct_answer": "Suessa Aurunca"
    },
    {
      "question": "What author was born in 180 BC at Suessa Aurunca?",
      "options": ["Lucilius", "Plautus", "Naevius", "Ennius"],
      "correct_answer": "Lucilius"
    },
    {
      "question": "In what year did Lucilius die?",
      "options": ["102 BC", "120 BC", "110 BC", "90 BC"],
      "correct_answer": "102 BC"
    },
    {
      "question": "What author established hexameter as the meter of Roman satire?",
      "options": ["Lucilius", "Horace", "Juvenal", "Persius"],
      "correct_answer": "Lucilius"
    },
    {
      "question": "What meter did Lucilius establish as the meter of Roman satire?",
      "options": ["Dactylic Hexameter", "Iambic Pentameter", "Trochaic Tetrameter", "Anapestic Dimeter"],
      "correct_answer": "Dactylic Hexameter"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who was the first Latin writer to focus exclusively on Satire?",
      "options": ["Lucilius", "Horace", "Juvenal", "Persius"],
      "correct_answer": "Lucilius"
    },
    {
      "question": "What genre was Lucilius the first to focus exclusively on?",
      "options": ["Satire", "Tragedy", "Epic", "Lyric"],
      "correct_answer": "Satire"
    },
    {
      "question": "What was the title of Lucilius' collection of Satires?",
      "options": ["Sermones", "Satires", "Epistulae", "Carmina"],
      "correct_answer": "Sermones"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the alternate title of Lucilius' Sermones?",
      "options": ["Ludus ac Sermones", "De Agri Cultura", "De Bello Gallico", "Adelphi"],
      "correct_answer": "Ludus ac Sermones"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who wrote a 30 book collection of Satires called Sermones?",
      "options": ["Lucilius", "Horace", "Juvenal", "Persius"],
      "correct_answer": "Lucilius"
    },
    {
      "question": "How many books of Satires made up Lucilius' Sermones?",
      "options": ["30", "12", "24", "15"],
      "correct_answer": "30"
    },
    {
      "question": "What author did Horace call his lantern for his influence in Satire?",
      "options": ["Lucilius", "Juvenal", "Persius", "Plautus"],
      "correct_answer": "Lucilius"
    },
    {
      "question": "What author called Lucilius his lantern for his influence in Satire?",
      "options": ["Horace", "Juvenal", "Persius", "Plautus"],
      "correct_answer": "Horace"
    },
    {
      "question": "Whose satires on a trip to Brundisium and an encounter with a bore were models for Horace?",
      "options": ["Lucilius", "Plautus", "Naevius", "Ennius"],
      "correct_answer": "Lucilius"
    },
    {
      "question": "What author was the great-uncle of Pompey the Great?",
      "options": ["Lucilius", "Plautus", "Naevius", "Ennius"],
      "correct_answer": "Lucilius"
    },
    {
      "question": "What author was called the 'Christian Cicero'?",
      "options": ["Lactantius", "Jerome", "Arnobius", "Cicero"],
      "correct_answer": "Lactantius"
    },
    {
      "question": "What honorific title was given to Lactantius because of his writing style?",
      "options": ["Christian Cicero", "Father of the Church", "Doctor of the Church", "Apostle of the Gauls"],
      "correct_answer": "Christian Cicero"
    },
    {
      "question": "What work of Lactantius justified Christianity to educated Pagans?",
      "options": ["Institutiones Divinae", "De Mortibus Persecutorum", "Divina Commedia", "Apologia"],
      "correct_answer": "Institutiones Divinae"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the Latin title of Lactantius' Divine Institutions?",
      "options": ["Institutiones Divinae", "De Divinitate", "Divinae Institutiones", "De Fide"],
      "correct_answer": "Institutiones Divinae"
    },
    {
      "question": "To which emperor did Lactantius dedicate his Institutiones Divinae?",
      "options": ["Constantine", "Maxentius", "Diocletian", "Julian"],
      "correct_answer": "Constantine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which work did Lactantius dedicate to the emperor Constantine?",
      "options": ["Institutiones Divinae", "De Mortibus Persecutorum", "Divina Commedia", "De Ira"],
      "correct_answer": "Institutiones Divinae"
    },
    {
      "question": "By what writer of the Late Republic was Lactantius' style greatly influenced?",
      "options": ["Cicero", "Sallust", "Livy", "Caesar"],
      "correct_answer": "Cicero"
    },
    {
      "question": "What Numidian rhetorician was Lactantius' teacher?",
      "options": ["Arnobius", "Tertullian", "Augustine", "Clement"],
      "correct_answer": "Arnobius"
    },
    {
      "question": "What pupil of Arnobius wrote the Institutiones Divinae?",
      "options": ["Lactantius", "Jerome", "Augustine", "Hilary"],
      "correct_answer": "Lactantius"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which author tutored Constantine's son Crispus?",
      "options": ["Lactantius", "Jerome", "Arnobius", "Augustine"],
      "correct_answer": "Lactantius"
    },
    {
      "question": "What son of Constantine did Lactantius tutor?",
      "options": ["Crispus", "Constantius", "Constans", "Julian"],
      "correct_answer": "Crispus"
    },
    {
      "question": "What was Jerome's full name?",
      "options": ["Sophronius Eusebius Heironymus", "Gaius Valerius Catullus", "Publius Ovidius Naso", "Marcus Tullius Cicero"],
      "correct_answer": "Sophronius Eusebius Heironymus"
    },
    {
      "question": "In what Dalmatian city was Jerome born?",
      "options": ["Stridon", "Salona", "Dubrovnik", "Split"],
      "correct_answer": "Stridon"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which author was born at Stridon in Dalmatia?",
      "options": ["Jerome", "Lactantius", "Augustine", "Tertullian"],
      "correct_answer": "Jerome"
    },
    {
      "question": "In what year was Jerome born at Stridon?",
      "options": ["347 AD", "350 AD", "360 AD", "345 AD"],
      "correct_answer": "347 AD"
    },
    {
      "question": "In what year did Jerome die at Bethlehem?",
      "options": ["420 AD", "410 AD", "430 AD", "415 AD"],
      "correct_answer": "420 AD"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which work of Jerome was a Latin translation of the Bible for common people?",
      "options": ["Vulgate", "Septuagint", "Peshitta", "Vita Patrum"],
      "correct_answer": "Vulgate"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the Latin title of Jerome's Vulgate?",
      "options": ["Biblia Vulgata", "Biblia Sacra", "Biblia Latina", "Vulgata Testamenta"],
      "correct_answer": "Biblia Vulgata"
    },
    {
      "question": "Who translated the Hebrew Old Testament and Greek New Testament into Latin?",
      "options": ["Jerome", "Lactantius", "Augustine", "Hilary"],
      "correct_answer": "Jerome"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which author translated the Bible into Latin?",
      "options": ["Jerome", "Clement", "Tertullian", "Irenaeus"],
      "correct_answer": "Jerome"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which work of Jerome covers the lives of 135 Christian authors from St. Peter to himself?",
      "options": ["De Viris Illustribus", "Chronica", "Vita Patrum", "Adversus Haereses"],
      "correct_answer": "De Viris Illustribus"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which Christian author wrote a De Viris Illustribus which covers the lives of 135 Christian authors, from St. Peter to Jerome himself?",
      "options": ["Jerome", "Augustine", "Clement", "Eusebius"],
      "correct_answer": "Jerome"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which work of Jerome is a historical treatise from Constantine to the death of Valens?",
      "options": ["Chronica", "De Viris Illustribus", "Vulgate", "Apologia"],
      "correct_answer": "Chronica"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which Christian author wrote a Chronica which details history from Constantine to the death of Valens?",
      "options": ["Jerome", "Augustine", "Eusebius", "Irenaeus"],
      "correct_answer": "Jerome"
    },
    {
        "question": "What group joined the horses to Apollo/Sol's chariot when Phaethon drove it?",
        "options": ["Horae", "Muses", "Graces", "Fates"],
        "correct_answer": "Horae"
    },
    {
        "question": "What did Apollo warn Phaethon not to do?",
        "options": ["Not to go too high or too low", "Not to let go of the reins", "Not to drive the chariot at night", "Not to drive too fast"],
        "correct_answer": "Not to go too high or too low"
    },
    {
        "question": "What Latin phrase came from Apollo warning Phaethon not to go too high or too low?",
        "options": ["medio tutissimus ibis", "in medio tutissimus", "medio in tutissimus", "medio tutus ibit"],
        "correct_answer": "medio tutissimus ibis"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who were the 4 horses who drove Apollo's chariot?",
        "options": ["Pyrois, Eous, Aethon, Phlegon", "Aethon, Pyrois, Eous, Phlegon", "Phlegon, Aethon, Pyrois, Eous", "Eous, Phlegon, Pyrois, Aethon"],
        "correct_answer": "Pyrois, Eous, Aethon, Phlegon"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who were Pyrois, Eous, Aethon, and Phlegon?",
        "options": ["The horses who drove Apollo's chariot", "The Titans who challenged Zeus", "The Nymphs who guarded the forest", "The giants who fought the gods"],
        "correct_answer": "The horses who drove Apollo's chariot"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which constellation scared Phaethon and resulted in him letting go of the reins?",
        "options": ["Scorpio", "Orion", "Leo", "Virgo"],
        "correct_answer": "Scorpio"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was scared by the constellation Scorpio?",
        "options": ["Phaethon", "Apollo", "Helios", "Hercules"],
        "correct_answer": "Phaethon"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which people became dark-skinned as a result of Phaethon's actions?",
        "options": ["Ethiopians", "Libyans", "Egyptians", "Arabs"],
        "correct_answer": "Ethiopians"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who caused Ethiopians to be dark-skinned and the Libyan desert to be created?",
        "options": ["Phaethon", "Apollo", "Zeus", "Hades"],
        "correct_answer": "Phaethon"
    },
    {
        "question": "What desert was created after Phaethon crashed?",
        "options": ["Libyan Desert", "Sahara Desert", "Gobi Desert", "Kalahari Desert"],
        "correct_answer": "Libyan Desert"
    },
    {
        "question": "What body of water hid its head after Phaethon crashed?",
        "options": ["Nile River", "Tiber River", "Euphrates River", "Jordan River"],
        "correct_answer": "Nile River"
    },
    {
        "question": "What does the Nile hiding its head explain?",
        "options": ["Nile Delta", "Nile Falls", "Nile Basin", "Nile Source"],
        "correct_answer": "Nile Delta"
    },
    {
        "question": "How many days did Apollo allow to go by without the sun?",
        "options": ["1", "3", "7", "10"],
        "correct_answer": "1"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who allowed one day to go by without the sun after Phaethon crashed?",
        "options": ["Apollo", "Zeus", "Helios", "Hermes"],
        "correct_answer": "Apollo"
    },
    {
        "question": "What group do Phaethusa and Lampetie belong to?",
        "options": ["Heliades", "Naiads", "Muses", "Charites"],
        "correct_answer": "Heliades"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who runs back and forth trying in vain to give her daughters a last kiss as they are turned into poplar trees?",
        "options": ["Clymene", "Leto", "Rhea", "Demeter"],
        "correct_answer": "Clymene"
    },
    {
        "question": "What does Clymene try to pull off of her daughter's bodies as they are turned into poplar trees?",
        "options": ["Bark", "Leaves", "Branches", "Fruit"],
        "correct_answer": "Bark"
    },
    {
        "question": "What bird refuses to fly into the sky, holding a grudge against Jupiter for killing Phaethon?",
        "options": ["Swan", "Eagle", "Raven", "Owl"],
        "correct_answer": "Swan"
    },
    {
        "question": "Why do swans refuse to fly in the sky?",
        "options": ["Because Jupiter killed Phaethon", "Because they are mourning Phaethon", "Because they are cursed", "Because they are injured"],
        "correct_answer": "Because Jupiter killed Phaethon"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who does Apollo blame for the death of Phaethon?",
        "options": ["The horses", "Himself", "Zeus", "Phaethon"],
        "correct_answer": "The horses"
    },
    {
        "question": "What did Ovid call Callisto?",
        "options": ["The Nonacrian maiden", "The Arcadian nymph", "The Thessalian goddess", "The Delian maiden"],
        "correct_answer": "The Nonacrian maiden"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was referred to as the Nonacrian maiden by Ovid?",
        "options": ["Callisto", "Daphne", "Io", "Europa"],
        "correct_answer": "Callisto"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whose eyes decorated Juno's peacocks?",
        "options": ["Argus", "Aegis", "Atlas", "Cerberus"],
        "correct_answer": "Argus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Argus's eyes decorated what animal?",
        "options": ["Peacock", "Eagle", "Swan", "Falcon"],
        "correct_answer": "Peacock"
    },
    {
        "question": "Juno's peacocks are compared to what bird?",
        "options": ["The raven", "The dove", "The owl", "The eagle"],
        "correct_answer": "The raven"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the first to notice Coronis committing adultery with Ischys?",
        "options": ["The raven", "The owl", "The crow", "The eagle"],
        "correct_answer": "The raven"
    },
    {
        "question": "What was the crow sometimes called?",
        "options": ["Cornix", "Rara", "Corydon", "Corvus"],
        "correct_answer": "Cornix"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was sometimes called Cornix?",
        "options": ["The crow", "The raven", "The vulture", "The eagle"],
        "correct_answer": "The crow"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the red-haired daughter of Chiron and Chariclo?",
        "options": ["Ocyroe", "Chione", "Melanippe", "Psyche"],
        "correct_answer": "Ocyroe"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who were the parents of Ocyroe?",
        "options": ["Chiron and Chariclo", "Apollo and Daphne", "Zeus and Leto", "Hermes and Aphrodite"],
        "correct_answer": "Chiron and Chariclo"
    },
    {
        "question": "What was Ocyroe turned into after the gods got mad at her for revealing too much?",
        "options": ["Horse", "Tree", "Stone", "Mountain"],
        "correct_answer": "Horse"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was turned into a horse for revealing too much?",
        "options": ["Ocyroe", "Io", "Callisto", "Arachne"],
        "correct_answer": "Ocyroe"
    },
    {
        "question": "What does Mercury bribe Battus with in order for him to not tell Apollo that he stole his cattle?",
        "options": ["A bright-white cow", "A golden lamb", "A silver goat", "A blue horse"],
        "correct_answer": "A bright-white cow"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who bribes Battus with a bright-white cow?",
        "options": ["Mercury", "Apollo", "Zeus", "Hermes"],
        "correct_answer": "Mercury"
    },
    {
        "question": "What does Battus say after promising not to tell anyone?",
        "options": ["This stone will snitch before I do", "I swear by the gods", "Not a word will escape my lips", "I am loyal to my oath"],
        "correct_answer": "This stone will snitch before I do"
    },
    {
        "question": "What old man in mythology said 'this stone will snitch before I do'?",
        "options": ["Battus", "Nestor", "Tiresias", "Chiron"],
        "correct_answer": "Battus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What does Mercury bribe Battus with while transformed as an old man?",
        "options": ["A bull and a cow", "A horse and a goat", "A sheep and a lamb", "A calf and a pig"],
        "correct_answer": "A bull and a cow"
    },
    {
        "question": "What place, a cold and dismal place with no light or wind, did Minerva visit?",
        "options": ["Abode of Envy", "Underworld", "Cave of Shadows", "Elysian Fields"],
        "correct_answer": "Abode of Envy"
    },
    {
        "question": "What was Envy eating when she saw the beautiful Minerva?",
        "options": ["Snake meat", "Roasted goat", "Flesh of a lion", "Boiled fish"],
        "correct_answer": "Snake meat"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who's described as pale, emaciated, crooked-eyed, teeth foul with mold, full of poisonous gall, never smiling except at someone else's pain, and always tortured by others' successes?",
        "options": ["Envy", "Nemesis", "Fury", "Despair"],
        "correct_answer": "Envy"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who entered Aglaurus's bedroom and infected her?",
        "options": ["Envy", "Aphrodite", "Hera", "Athena"],
        "correct_answer": "Envy"
    },
    {
        "question": "With what did Envy touch Aglaurus?",
        "options": ["Her rust-colored hand", "A cursed staff", "A venomous snake", "A darkened cloak"],
        "correct_answer": "Her rust-colored hand"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was infected by Envy?",
        "options": ["Aglaurus", "Eris", "Psyche", "Phaedra"],
        "correct_answer": "Aglaurus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who realizes she doesn't have hands when begging Argus for mercy?",
        "options": ["Io", "Daphne", "Callisto", "Eurydice"],
        "correct_answer": "Io"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whom did Io beg for mercy before realizing she had been turned into a cow?",
        "options": ["Argus", "Zeus", "Apollo", "Hades"],
        "correct_answer": "Argus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What came out of Io's mouth once she tried to talk to Argus?",
        "options": ["A moo", "A cry", "A roar", "A whistle"],
        "correct_answer": "A moo"
    },
    {
        "question": "What naiad's only difference with Diana was her bow of horn?",
        "options": ["Syrinx", "Euphrosyne", "Alcyone", "Nephele"],
        "correct_answer": "Syrinx"
    },
    {
        "question": "What material was Syrinx's bow made of?",
        "options": ["Horn", "Wood", "Silver", "Bronze"],
        "correct_answer": "Horn"
    },
    {
        "question": "What material was Diana's bow made of?",
        "options": ["Gold", "Ivory", "Copper", "Iron"],
        "correct_answer": "Gold"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was scared to talk, thinking she would moo, after first becoming human again?",
        "options": ["Io", "Callisto", "Eurydice", "Daphne"],
        "correct_answer": "Io"
    },
    {
        "question": "What did Io think would happen if she talked after becoming a human again?",
        "options": ["She would moo", "She would roar", "She would cry", "She would sing"],
        "correct_answer": "She would moo"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whose bones in mythology were turned into rocks?",
        "options": ["Echo", "Narcissus", "Psyche", "Eurydice"],
        "correct_answer": "Echo"
    },
    {
        "question": "What were Echo's bones turned into?",
        "options": ["Rocks", "Flowers", "Stars", "Trees"],
        "correct_answer": "Rocks"
    },
    {
        "question": "What was Narcissus's last word?",
        "options": ["Vale", "Ave", "Salve", "Farewell"],
        "correct_answer": "Vale"
    },
    {
        "question": "In mythology, what figure's last word was vale?",
        "options": ["Narcissus", "Orpheus", "Adonis", "Hyacinthus"],
        "correct_answer": "Narcissus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who repeats Narcissus's last word, vale?",
        "options": ["Echo", "Persephone", "Hera", "Athena"],
        "correct_answer": "Echo"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who gazes at his reflection even in the underworld?",
        "options": ["Narcissus", "Orpheus", "Hades", "Achilles"],
        "correct_answer": "Narcissus"
    },
    {
        "question": "In which river in the underworld does Narcissus gaze at his reflection?",
        "options": ["Styx", "Lethe", "Acheron", "Cocytus"],
        "correct_answer": "Styx"
    },
    {
        "question": "On which island does Opheltes find a young drunk boy?",
        "options": ["Chios", "Lesbos", "Samos", "Rhodes"],
        "correct_answer": "Chios"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who finds a young drunk boy on Chios?",
        "options": ["Opheltes", "Achilles", "Odysseus", "Theseus"],
        "correct_answer": "Opheltes"
    },
    {
        "question": "What was Pyramus's blood streaming out of him compared to?",
        "options": ["A pipe bursting", "A river flooding", "A broken dam", "A leaking faucet"],
        "correct_answer": "A pipe bursting"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whose blood streaming out of him was compared to a pipe bursting?",
        "options": ["Pyramus", "Thisbe", "Narcissus", "Adonis"],
        "correct_answer": "Pyramus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was a 7th generation descendant of Belus?",
        "options": ["Orchamus", "Perseus", "Heracles", "Theseus"],
        "correct_answer": "Orchamus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Orchamus was a 7th generation descendant of what man?",
        "options": ["Belus", "Zeus", "Poseidon", "Apollo"],
        "correct_answer": "Belus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the mother of Leucothoe?",
        "options": ["Eurynome", "Leto", "Rhea", "Hera"],
        "correct_answer": "Eurynome"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was Eurynome the mother of?",
        "options": ["Leucothoe", "Medusa", "Eurydice", "Callisto"],
        "correct_answer": "Leucothoe"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who takes the form of Eurynome to enter Leucothoe's bed chamber?",
        "options": ["Sol", "Zeus", "Hermes", "Apollo"],
        "correct_answer": "Sol"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whose form did Sol take in order to enter Leucothoe's bed chamber?",
        "options": ["Eurynome (her mother)", "Aphrodite", "Hera", "Athena"],
        "correct_answer": "Eurynome (her mother)"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who's described as a marble statue except for the fact that her hair waves in the breeze and tears stream from her eyes?",
        "options": ["Andromeda", "Psyche", "Hecuba", "Polyxena"],
        "correct_answer": "Andromeda"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whose head was placed on seaweed which turned into coral?",
        "options": ["Medusa", "Arachne", "Echidna", "Sphinx"],
        "correct_answer": "Medusa"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who placed Medusa's head on seaweed that turned into coral?",
        "options": ["Perseus", "Theseus", "Hercules", "Odysseus"],
        "correct_answer": "Perseus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where was Medusa's head placed by Perseus?",
        "options": ["Seaweed", "A rock", "A tree", "A riverbank"],
        "correct_answer": "Seaweed"
    },
    {
        "question": "What was the seaweed that Medusa's head was placed on turned into?",
        "options": ["Coral", "Pebbles", "Sand", "Shells"],
        "correct_answer": "Coral"
    },
    {
        "question": "What city in Thrace did Pyreneus rule in?",
        "options": ["Daulis", "Ephesus", "Macedonia", "Athens"],
        "correct_answer": "Daulis"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the king of Daulis?",
        "options": ["Pyreneus", "Midas", "Euryalus", "Pylades"],
        "correct_answer": "Pyreneus"
    },
    {
        "question": "How does Pyreneus die?",
        "options": ["He jumps off a high balcony", "He is struck by lightning", "He is poisoned", "He drowns in a river"],
        "correct_answer": "He jumps off a high balcony"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who kills himself by jumping off a high balcony?",
        "options": ["Pyreneus", "Ajax", "Agamemnon", "Perseus"],
        "correct_answer": "Pyreneus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What group sings about the Gigantomachy and the fight with Typhon?",
        "options": ["Pierides", "Muses", "Siren", "Graces"],
        "correct_answer": "Pierides"
    },
    {
        "question": "What did Jupiter change into when fleeing to Egypt?",
        "options": ["Ram", "Eagle", "Lion", "Horse"],
        "correct_answer": "Ram"
    },
    {
        "question": "What deity changed into a ram when fleeing to Egypt?",
        "options": ["Jupiter", "Apollo", "Neptune", "Mars"],
        "correct_answer": "Jupiter"
    },
    {
        "question": "What did Apollo change into when fleeing to Egypt?",
        "options": ["Crow", "Dolphin", "Wolf", "Horse"],
        "correct_answer": "Crow"
    },
    {
        "question": "What deity changed into a crow when fleeing to Egypt?",
        "options": ["Apollo", "Jupiter", "Mercury", "Bacchus"],
        "correct_answer": "Apollo"
    },
    {
        "question": "What did Bacchus change into when fleeing to Egypt?",
        "options": ["Goat", "Bear", "Tiger", "Elephant"],
        "correct_answer": "Goat"
    },
    {
        "question": "What deity changed into a goat when fleeing to Egypt?",
        "options": ["Bacchus", "Venus", "Juno", "Neptune"],
        "correct_answer": "Bacchus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What did Diana change into when fleeing to Egypt?",
        "options": ["Cat", "Deer", "Rabbit", "Swan"],
        "correct_answer": "Cat"
    },
    {
        "question": "What deity changed into a cat when fleeing to Egypt?",
        "options": ["Diana", "Hera", "Aphrodite", "Minerva"],
        "correct_answer": "Diana"
    },
    {
        "question": "What did Juno change into when fleeing to Egypt?",
        "options": ["Cow", "Horse", "Eagle", "Lion"],
        "correct_answer": "Cow"
    },
    {
        "question": "What deity changed into a cow when fleeing to Egypt?",
        "options": ["Juno", "Venus", "Hera", "Athena"],
        "correct_answer": "Juno"
    },
    {
        "question": "What did Venus change into when fleeing to Egypt?",
        "options": ["Fish", "Dove", "Swan", "Bee"],
        "correct_answer": "Fish"
    },
    {
        "question": "What deity changed into a fish when fleeing to Egypt?",
        "options": ["Venus", "Hera", "Aphrodite", "Demeter"],
        "correct_answer": "Venus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What did Mercury change into when fleeing to Egypt?",
        "options": ["Ibis", "Hawk", "Falcon", "Bat"],
        "correct_answer": "Ibis"
    },
    {
        "question": "What deity was changed into an ibis when fleeing to Egypt?",
        "options": ["Mercury", "Apollo", "Jupiter", "Mars"],
        "correct_answer": "Mercury"
    },
    {
        "question": "At what lake was Proserpina picking flowers when Pluto snatched her away?",
        "options": ["Pergus", "Nemi", "Avernus", "Lerna"],
        "correct_answer": "Pergus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was picking flowers at the lake Pergus?",
        "options": ["Proserpina", "Clytemenestra", "Helen", "Andromeda"],
        "correct_answer": "Proserpina"
    },
    {
        "question": "What nymph tries to stop Pluto from snatching away from Proserpina?",
        "options": ["Cyane", "Arethusa", "Eurydice", "Daphne"],
        "correct_answer": "Cyane"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who does Cyane try to stop?",
        "options": ["Pluto", "Zeus", "Apollo", "Hermes"],
        "correct_answer": "Pluto"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was Cyane's husband?",
        "options": ["Anapis", "Oceanus", "Cronus", "Atlas"],
        "correct_answer": "Anapis"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the wife of Anapis?",
        "options": ["Cyane", "Leto", "Rhea", "Dione"],
        "correct_answer": "Cyane"
    },
    {
        "question": "What does Cyane melt into?",
        "options": ["A pool of water", "A stone", "A flower", "A river"],
        "correct_answer": "A pool of water"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who melts into a pool of water?",
        "options": ["Cyane", "Echo", "Narcissus", "Arachne"],
        "correct_answer": "Cyane"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who comes into the house of an old woman named Misme?",
        "options": ["Ceres", "Juno", "Venus", "Diana"],
        "correct_answer": "Ceres"
    },
    {
        "question": "Into what old woman's house does Ceres come into?",
        "options": ["Misme", "Hecate", "Eurynome", "Clymene"],
        "correct_answer": "Misme"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where does Ceres find Cyane?",
        "options": ["Sicily", "Crete", "Athens", "Rome"],
        "correct_answer": "Sicily"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who does Ceres find at Sicily?",
        "options": ["Cyane", "Proserpina", "Arachne", "Echo"],
        "correct_answer": "Cyane"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who finds Cyane at Sicily?",
        "options": ["Ceres", "Jupiter", "Apollo", "Mercury"],
        "correct_answer": "Ceres"
    },
    {
        "question": "What does Cyane give to Ceres in Sicily?",
        "options": ["Proserpina's girdle", "A golden apple", "A magic wand", "A bouquet of flowers"],
        "correct_answer": "Proserpina's girdle"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who gives Proserpina's girdle to Ceres in Sicily?",
        "options": ["Cyane", "Arethusa", "Diana", "Juno"],
        "correct_answer": "Cyane"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who does Diana cover in a cloud?",
        "options": ["Arethusa", "Callisto", "Eurydice", "Psyche"],
        "correct_answer": "Arethusa"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who covered Arethusa in a cloud?",
        "options": ["Diana", "Venus", "Athena", "Juno"],
        "correct_answer": "Diana"
    },
    {
        "question": "What does Diana cover Arethusa in?",
        "options": ["A cloud", "A veil", "A mist", "A cloak"],
        "correct_answer": "A cloud"
    },
    {
        "question": "What couple were transformed into mountains for calling themselves Jupiter and Juno?",
        "options": ["Haemus and Rhodope", "Orpheus and Eurydice", "Phaethon and Clymene", "Aeneas and Dido"],
        "correct_answer": "Haemus and Rhodope"
    },
    {
        "question": "What were Haemus and Rhodope transformed into?",
        "options": ["mountains", "rivers", "forests", "stars"],
        "correct_answer": "mountains"
    },
    {
        "question": "What did Haemus and Rhodope call themselves?",
        "options": ["Jupiter and Juno", "Apollo and Artemis", "Neptune and Venus", "Mars and Bellona"],
        "correct_answer": "Jupiter and Juno"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who claimed that her hair was more beautiful than Juno's?",
        "options": ["Antigone", "Leda", "Cassiopeia", "Hera"],
        "correct_answer": "Antigone"
    },
    {
        "question": "What was Antigone's hair full of after claiming her hair was more beautiful than Juno's?",
        "options": ["snakes", "flowers", "golden strands", "jewels"],
        "correct_answer": "snakes"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whose hair became full of snakes?",
        "options": ["Antigone", "Medusa", "Eurydice", "Syrinx"],
        "correct_answer": "Antigone"
    },
    {
        "question": "What animal, the enemy of snakes, was Antigone turned into?",
        "options": ["stork", "eagle", "hawk", "lion"],
        "correct_answer": "stork"
    },
    {
        "question": "What Assyrian king saw the limbs of his daughters transform into the steps of a temple?",
        "options": ["Cinyras", "Nimrod", "Sennacherib", "Ashurbanipal"],
        "correct_answer": "Cinyras"
    },
    {
        "question": "What were the daughters of Cinyras turned into?",
        "options": ["steps of a temple", "statues", "trees", "rivers"],
        "correct_answer": "steps of a temple"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where was Cinyras a king of?",
        "options": ["Assyria", "Cyprus", "Babylon", "Egypt"],
        "correct_answer": "Assyria"
    },
    {
        "question": "In what form does Jupiter pursue Asteria?",
        "options": ["eagle", "serpent", "lion", "dolphin"],
        "correct_answer": "eagle"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who does Jupiter pursue in the form of an eagle?",
        "options": ["Asteria", "Callisto", "Io", "Leda"],
        "correct_answer": "Asteria"
    },
    {
        "question": "In what form does Jupiter pursue Mnemosyne?",
        "options": ["shepherd", "dolphin", "wolf", "horse"],
        "correct_answer": "shepherd"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who does Jupiter pursue in the form of a shepherd?",
        "options": ["Mnemosyne", "Cybele", "Echo", "Psyche"],
        "correct_answer": "Mnemosyne"
    },
    {
        "question": "In what form does Neptune pursue Iphimedeia?",
        "options": ["Enipeus river", "a lion", "a whirlwind", "a stag"],
        "correct_answer": "Enipeus river"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who does Neptune pursue in the form of the Enipeus river? (not Tyro)",
        "options": ["Iphimedeia", "Thetis", "Amphitrite", "Medusa"],
        "correct_answer": "Iphimedeia"
    },
    {
        "question": "In what form does Neptune pursue Medusa?",
        "options": ["bird", "serpent", "horse", "lion"],
        "correct_answer": "bird"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who does Neptune pursue in the form of a bird?",
        "options": ["Medusa", "Amphitrite", "Hera", "Leto"],
        "correct_answer": "Medusa"
    },
    {
        "question": "In what form does Apollo pursue Isse?",
        "options": ["shepherd", "horse", "eagle", "serpent"],
        "correct_answer": "shepherd"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who does Apollo pursue in the form of a shepherd?",
        "options": ["Isse", "Callisto", "Hecuba", "Cyrene"],
        "correct_answer": "Isse"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the father of Isse?",
        "options": ["Macareus", "Epopeus", "Cinyas", "Tantalus"],
        "correct_answer": "Macareus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the daughter of Macareus that was pursued by Apollo?",
        "options": ["Isse", "Arethusa", "Ariadne", "Eurydice"],
        "correct_answer": "Isse"
    },
    {
        "question": "What does Minerva spray Arachne with?",
        "options": ["nightshade", "poison", "mist", "nectar"],
        "correct_answer": "nightshade"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was sprayed with nightshade and became a spider?",
        "options": ["Arachne", "Medusa", "Eurydice", "Syrinx"],
        "correct_answer": "Arachne"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who tells the Thebans to sacrifice to Latona?",
        "options": ["Manto", "Cassandra", "Orpheus", "Tiresias"],
        "correct_answer": "Manto"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who does Manto tell to sacrifice to Latona?",
        "options": ["Thebans", "Athenians", "Spartans", "Corinthians"],
        "correct_answer": "Thebans"
    },
    {
        "question": "To whom does Manto tell the Thebans to sacrifice to?",
        "options": ["Latona", "Apollo", "Diana", "Jupiter"],
        "correct_answer": "Latona"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who were Athens at war with when kings from all over Greece came to console the Thebans?",
        "options": ["barbarians", "Persians", "Romans", "Spartans"],
        "correct_answer": "barbarians"
    },
    {
        "question": "What city was at war with barbarians when kings from all over Greece came to console the Thebans?",
        "options": ["Athens", "Sparta", "Corinth", "Thebes"],
        "correct_answer": "Athens"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who disguised as a Bacchant during a festival of Bacchus and pretends to go crazy?",
        "options": ["Procne", "Philomela", "Psyche", "Eurydice"],
        "correct_answer": "Procne"
    },
    {
        "question": "During whose festival does Procne pretend to go crazy?",
        "options": ["Bacchus", "Apollo", "Jupiter", "Neptune"],
        "correct_answer": "Bacchus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Why does Procne pretend to go crazy during a festival of Bacchus?",
        "options": ["to rescue Philomela", "to escape Tereus", "to punish the Furies", "to honor her father"],
        "correct_answer": "to rescue Philomela"
    },
    {
        "question": "What group attended the marriage of Procne and Tereus?",
        "options": ["Furies", "Muses", "Nymphs", "Satyrs"],
        "correct_answer": "Furies"
    },
    {
        "question": "What did the Furies carry instead of wedding torches?",
        "options": ["funeral torches", "flames", "wreaths", "baskets of flowers"],
        "correct_answer": "funeral torches"
    },
    {
        "question": "What animal sat on the roof of Procne and Tereus's bedchamber?",
        "options": ["owl", "eagle", "raven", "dove"],
        "correct_answer": "owl"
    },
    {
        "question": "On top of what couple's bedchamber did an owl sit?",
        "options": ["Procne and Tereus", "Orpheus and Eurydice", "Jason and Medea", "Aeneas and Dido"],
        "correct_answer": "Procne and Tereus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whose wedding did the Furies attend?",
        "options": ["Procne and Tereus", "Hercules and Deianira", "Paris and Helen", "Theseus and Ariadne"],
        "correct_answer": "Procne and Tereus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where did Cerambus live?",
        "options": ["Othrys", "Olympus", "Pindus", "Pelion"],
        "correct_answer": "Othrys"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who came to Othrys after the Great Flood?",
        "options": ["Cerambus", "Deucalion", "Prometheus", "Epimetheus"],
        "correct_answer": "Cerambus"
    },
    {
        "question": "At what city is there a snake that turns to stone?",
        "options": ["Pitane", "Athens", "Corinth", "Sparta"],
        "correct_answer": "Pitane"
    },
    {
        "question": "What animal is turned to stone at Pitane?",
        "options": ["snake", "horse", "deer", "eagle"],
        "correct_answer": "snake"
    },
    {
        "question": "At what forest does Bacchus transform a bull stolen by his son into a deer, and where the father of Corythus is buried?",
        "options": ["Ida", "Erymanthos", "Pelion", "Pindus"],
        "correct_answer": "Ida"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who transforms a bull stolen by his son into a deer in the forest of Ida?",
        "options": ["Bacchus", "Apollo", "Jupiter", "Neptune"],
        "correct_answer": "Bacchus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What animal, which was stolen by Bacchus' son, was transformed into a deer to hide the theft?",
        "options": ["bull", "sheep", "goat", "horse"],
        "correct_answer": "bull"
    },
    {
        "question": "Into what animal was the bull, which Bacchus' son stole, transformed?",
        "options": ["deer", "horse", "wolf", "lion"],
        "correct_answer": "deer"
    },
    {
        "question": "What creature scares an entire field with its barking?",
        "options": ["Maera", "Cerberus", "Scylla", "Chimera"],
        "correct_answer": "Maera"
    },
    {
        "question": "What island's women claimed they were more beautiful than Venus and grew horns?",
        "options": ["Cos", "Samos", "Rhodes", "Crete"],
        "correct_answer": "Cos"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the capital of the island of Ceus?",
        "options": ["Carthaea", "Eryx", "Delos", "Knossos"],
        "correct_answer": "Carthaea"
    },
    {
        "question": "Carthaea is the capital of WHAT island?",
        "options": ["Ceus", "Crete", "Lesbos", "Chios"],
        "correct_answer": "Ceus"
    },
    {
        "question": "On what island does Alcidamas’ daughter Ctesylla become a dove shortly after her marriage to Hermochares?",
        "options": ["Ceus", "Cyprus", "Thasos", "Lesbos"],
        "correct_answer": "Ceus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whose daughter becomes a dove shortly after her marriage to Hermochares?",
        "options": ["Alcidamas", "Oedipus", "Menelaus", "Tantalus"],
        "correct_answer": "Alcidamas"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was transformed into a dove after her marriage to Hermochares?",
        "options": ["Ctesylla", "Andromeda", "Eurydice", "Psyche"],
        "correct_answer": "Ctesylla"
    },
    {
        "question": "Into what did Ctesylla transform shortly after her marriage to Hermochares?",
        "options": ["dove", "flower", "fish", "star"],
        "correct_answer": "dove"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the father of Ctesylla?",
        "options": ["Alcidamas", "Macareus", "Cybele", "Nereus"],
        "correct_answer": "Alcidamas"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was married to Ctesylla?",
        "options": ["Hermochares", "Theseus", "Eros", "Perseus"],
        "correct_answer": "Hermochares"
    },
    {
        "question": "In what city does Combe, daughter of Ophius, fly away from the attacks of her son?",
        "options": ["Pleuron", "Argos", "Mycenae", "Thebes"],
        "correct_answer": "Pleuron"
    },
    {
        "question": "What daughter of Ophius flies away from the attacks of her son?",
        "options": ["Combe", "Leto", "Eos", "Hestia"],
        "correct_answer": "Combe"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the father of Combe, a native of Pleuron?",
        "options": ["Ophius", "Aegeus", "Epopeus", "Tantalus"],
        "correct_answer": "Ophius"
    },
    {
        "question": "What river had a grandson who was turned into a seal by Apollo?",
        "options": ["Cephisus", "Alpheus", "Peneus", "Achelous"],
        "correct_answer": "Cephisus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What was the grandson of the river Cephisus transformed into?",
        "options": ["seal", "fish", "bird", "serpent"],
        "correct_answer": "seal"
    },
    {
        "question": "At what city does Eumelus see his son Botres turned into a bird?",
        "options": ["Thebes", "Athens", "Corinth", "Argos"],
        "correct_answer": "Thebes"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the father of Botres that saw him transformed into a bird?",
        "options": ["Eumelus", "Perseus", "Agamemnon", "Theseus"],
        "correct_answer": "Eumelus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What son of Eumelus of Thebes was transformed into a bird?",
        "options": ["Botres", "Philomela", "Euryalus", "Thyestes"],
        "correct_answer": "Botres"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who had been killed by his father with a firebrand for doing a bad job with a sacrifice to Apollo, after which Apollo turned him into a bird?",
        "options": ["Botres", "Aeneas", "Paris", "Orpheus"],
        "correct_answer": "Botres"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who killed his son Botres with a firebrand for doing a bad job with a sacrifice to Apollo?",
        "options": ["Eumelus", "Aegeus", "Minos", "Epopeus"],
        "correct_answer": "Eumelus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Into what was Botres transformed by Apollo after being killed with a firebrand for doing a bad job with a sacrifice to Apollo?",
        "options": ["bird", "fish", "serpent", "horse"],
        "correct_answer": "bird"
    },
    {
        "question": "What city's inhabitants may have been born from fungi?",
        "options": ["Corinth", "Athens", "Thebes", "Sparta"],
        "correct_answer": "Corinth"
    },
    {
        "question": "What Attic king had been turned into an eagle and his wife Phene became a vulture?",
        "options": ["Periphas", "Aegeus", "Pandion", "Thespius"],
        "correct_answer": "Periphas"
    },
    {
        "question": "Into what was Periphas the Attic king transformed?",
        "options": ["eagle", "lion", "horse", "deer"],
        "correct_answer": "eagle"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the wife of Periphas that was transformed into a vulture?",
        "options": ["Phene", "Antigone", "Eurydice", "Daphne"],
        "correct_answer": "Phene"
    },
    {
        "question": "Into what was Phene, the wife of Periphas, transformed?",
        "options": ["vulture", "serpent", "dove", "wolf"],
        "correct_answer": "vulture"
    },
    {
        "question": "The inhabitants of WHAT city had worshipped Periphas as Zeus, but Apollo persuaded Zeus not to kill them for this, since they had done nothing wrong themselves?",
        "options": ["Athens", "Corinth", "Thebes", "Argos"],
        "correct_answer": "Athens"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whom did the citizens of Athens honor as Zeus, causing Zeus to almost induce punishment until Apollo stopped him?",
        "options": ["Periphas", "Eumelus", "Theseus", "Hercules"],
        "correct_answer": "Periphas"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who covers herself in a magical cloud and flees from Athens?",
        "options": ["Medea", "Ariadne", "Psyche", "Cassandra"],
        "correct_answer": "Medea"
    },
    {
        "question": "Clytus and Butes accompany WHOM to Aeacus' home to ask for assistance against Minos?",
        "options": ["Cephalus", "Eumelus", "Perseus", "Heracles"],
        "correct_answer": "Cephalus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What 2 sons of Pallas accompany Cephalus to Aeacus' home to ask for assistance against Minos?",
        "options": ["Clytus and Butes", "Aeneas and Dido", "Hector and Paris", "Achilles and Patroclus"],
        "correct_answer": "Clytus and Butes"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the father of Clytus and Butes?",
        "options": ["Pallas", "Aegeus", "Pandion", "Theseus"],
        "correct_answer": "Pallas"
    },
    {
        "question": "The dead citizens of what island were compared to rotten fruit or acorns falling off a tree when it gets shaken?",
        "options": ["Aegina", "Crete", "Lesbos", "Samos"],
        "correct_answer": "Aegina"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the dead citizens of Aegina compared to?",
        "options": ["rotten fruit and acorns", "fallen leaves", "dead branches", "broken stones"],
        "correct_answer": "rotten fruit and acorns"
    },
    {
        "question": "What island's citizens die mid prayer?",
        "options": ["Aegina", "Corinth", "Mykonos", "Delos"],
        "correct_answer": "Aegina"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who notices that Cephalus is carrying an unfamiliar-looking javelin with a gold tip?",
        "options": ["Phocus", "Minos", "Aeacus", "Aeneas"],
        "correct_answer": "Phocus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who carries a javelin with a gold tip?",
        "options": ["Cephalus", "Hercules", "Theseus", "Jason"],
        "correct_answer": "Cephalus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What city is also known as Alcathoe?",
        "options": ["Megara", "Thebes", "Corinth", "Athens"],
        "correct_answer": "Megara"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the name of Megara in Ovid?",
        "options": ["Alcathoe", "Eryx", "Antheia", "Lydia"],
        "correct_answer": "Alcathoe"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whose death occurs between the islands of Samos, Lebinthos, and Calymne?",
        "options": ["Icarus", "Perseus", "Orpheus", "Achilles"],
        "correct_answer": "Icarus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Because Diana caused the iron tip of his javelin to fall off, who does not wound the Calydonian boar despite the fact that he prayed to Apollo to hit it?",
        "options": ["Mopsus", "Atalanta", "Meleager", "Theseus"],
        "correct_answer": "Mopsus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What deity caused the iron tip of Mopsus' javelin to fall off, causing him to not wound the Calydonian boar despite the fact that he prayed to Apollo to hit it?",
        "options": ["Diana", "Apollo", "Venus", "Jupiter"],
        "correct_answer": "Diana"
    },
    {
        "question": "What did Mopsus fail to wound despite the fact that he prayed to Apollo to hit it?",
        "options": ["Calydonian Boar", "Lion", "Serpent", "Bull"],
        "correct_answer": "Calydonian Boar"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who trips on a tree root while following the Calydonian boar?",
        "options": ["Telamon", "Jason", "Meleager", "Atalanta"],
        "correct_answer": "Telamon"
    },
    {
        "question": "What creature does Jason accidentally kill during the Calydonian boar hunt?",
        "options": ["dog", "deer", "boar", "wolf"],
        "correct_answer": "dog"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is blocked by the Achelous river which was overflowing its banks; the river-god encourages him to stay the night in his home (made of pumice-stone and tufa, with moss on the floor and shell-fish on the ceiling?",
        "options": ["Theseus", "Perseus", "Heracles", "Theseus"],
        "correct_answer": "Theseus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What river's home was made of pumice-stone and tufa, with moss on the floor and shell-fish on the ceiling?",
        "options": ["Achelous", "Alpheus", "Peneus", "Acheron"],
        "correct_answer": "Achelous"
    },
    {
        "question": "According to Ovid, who was the father of Perimele, lover of Achelous?",
        "options": ["Hippodamas", "Pallas", "Eumelus", "Aegeus"],
        "correct_answer": "Hippodamas"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the daughter of Hippodamas that was pursued by a river?",
        "options": ["Perimele", "Arethusa", "Daphne", "Callisto"],
        "correct_answer": "Perimele"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who doesn’t believe Achelous’s story and claims the gods can’t actually transform people?",
        "options": ["Pirithous", "Theseus", "Jason", "Cadmus"],
        "correct_answer": "Pirithous"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who had sent Lelex to Phrygia, where he saw an oak and linden tree next to each other, and a swamp nearby, where there had once been habitable land?",
        "options": ["Pittheus", "Eumelus", "Thespius", "Aegeus"],
        "correct_answer": "Pittheus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was sent by Pittheus to Phrygia, where he saw an oak and linden tree next to each other, and a swamp nearby, where there had once been habitable land?",
        "options": ["Lelex", "Aeneas", "Theseus", "Jason"],
        "correct_answer": "Lelex"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who sends an Oread (mountain nymph) to visit the abode of Hunger (Fames) in order to afflict Erysichthon with eternal hunger?",
        "options": ["Ceres", "Diana", "Venus", "Jupiter"],
        "correct_answer": "Ceres"
    },
    {
        "question": "What type of nymph does Ceres send to visit the abode of Hunger (Fames) in order to afflict Erysichthon with eternal hunger?",
        "options": ["Oread", "Naiad", "Oceanid", "Dryad"],
        "correct_answer": "Oread"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whose home is visited by an Oread sent by Demeter in order to afflict Erysichthon with eternal hunger?",
        "options": ["Fames", "Erysichthon", "Persephone", "Apollo"],
        "correct_answer": "Fames"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who cannot visit Fames because they are opposites, since Fames lives in a barren land in Scythia near the Caucasus mountains, along with Cold (Frigus), Pallor (Pallor), and Shivering (Tremor)?",
        "options": ["Ceres", "Apollo", "Jupiter", "Neptune"],
        "correct_answer": "Ceres"
    },
    {
        "question": "Because she lives in a barren land in Scythia near the Caucasus mountains, along with Cold (Frigus), Pallor (Pallor), and Shivering (Tremor), WHO is the opposite of Ceres?",
        "options": ["Fames", "Venus", "Diana", "Hera"],
        "correct_answer": "Fames"
    },
    {
        "question": "In what region does Fames live?",
        "options": ["Scythia", "Arcadia", "Ionia", "Thessaly"],
        "correct_answer": "Scythia"
    },
    {
        "question": "Near what mountains does Fames live?",
        "options": ["Caucasus Mountains", "Olympus", "Pindus", "Ida"],
        "correct_answer": "Caucasus Mountains"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is described as shaggy-haired, hollowed-out eyes, pale, chapped lips, skin so hard and emaciated that you can see her innards, and no stomach?",
        "options": ["Fames", "Hecate", "Nyx", "Eris"],
        "correct_answer": "Fames"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who disguised herself as a fisherman to escape from her first master?",
        "options": ["Mestra", "Clytie", "Leto", "Eurydice"],
        "correct_answer": "Mestra"
    },
    {
        "question": "What did Mestra disguise as to escape from her first master?",
        "options": ["fisherman", "shepherd", "merchant", "slave"],
        "correct_answer": "fisherman"
    },
    {
        "question": "To what deity does Heracles sacrifice at Cape Cenaeum?",
        "options": ["Jupiter", "Apollo", "Neptune", "Mars"],
        "correct_answer": "Jupiter"
    },
    {
        "question": "What animal is believed to give birth through the mouth?",
        "options": ["weasel", "snake", "lizard", "cat"],
        "correct_answer": "weasel"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was transformed into an animal believed to give birth through the mouth?",
        "options": ["Galanthis", "Daphne", "Io", "Callisto"],
        "correct_answer": "Galanthis"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is called by the patronymic Pallantias, since she is sometimes said to be a daughter of the Titan Pallas?",
        "options": ["Aurora", "Athena", "Hera", "Artemis"],
        "correct_answer": "Aurora"
    },
    {
        "question": "What patronymic does Ovid give Aurora?",
        "options": ["Pallantias", "Herculea", "Apollonia", "Zeus"],
        "correct_answer": "Pallantias"
    },
    {
        "question": "What son of Apollo and Deione was believed by Minos to have been planning to rebel against him?",
        "options": ["Miletus", "Orpheus", "Aesculapius", "Hyacinthus"],
        "correct_answer": "Miletus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who has a dream where she “joins her body” with her brother?",
        "options": ["Byblis", "Phaedra", "Iphigenia", "Electra"],
        "correct_answer": "Byblis"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who has to remember to erase the word “sister” whenever she accidentally refers to herself in a letter she writes to her brother?",
        "options": ["Byblis", "Phaedra", "Sappho", "Ariadne"],
        "correct_answer": "Byblis"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who decided that the letter she wrote was read at a bad time by the slave to whom she had trusted?",
        "options": ["Byblis", "Clytemenestra", "Dido", "Phyllis"],
        "correct_answer": "Byblis"
    },
    {
        "question": "What type of nymphs transform Byblis into a spring?",
        "options": ["Lelegian nymphs", "Oceanid nymphs", "Dryad nymphs", "Naiad nymphs"],
        "correct_answer": "Lelegian nymphs"
    },
    {
        "question": "Lelegian nymphs transform WHOM into a spring?",
        "options": ["Byblis", "Io", "Syrinx", "Echo"],
        "correct_answer": "Byblis"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is accompanied by Anubis, Bubastis, Apis, Harpocrates, and Osiris when she tells Telethusa to raise the child with her husband Ligdus?",
        "options": ["Isis", "Hathor", "Nephthys", "Selene"],
        "correct_answer": "Isis"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the daughter of Telestes?",
        "options": ["Ianthe", "Phaedra", "Eurydice", "Helen"],
        "correct_answer": "Ianthe"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the father of Ianthe?",
        "options": ["Telestes", "Euryalus", "Hippodamas", "Perseus"],
        "correct_answer": "Telestes"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who says that her love is even weirder than Pasiphae falling in love with a bull?",
        "options": ["Iphis", "Myrrha", "Phyllis", "Scylla"],
        "correct_answer": "Iphis"
    },
    {
        "question": "Even the Furies cry because of WHOM?",
        "options": ["Orpheus", "Psyche", "Eurydice", "Narcissus"],
        "correct_answer": "Orpheus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whose astonishment is compared to the unnamed man who turned into stone out of fright from seeing Hercules bringing Cerberus into the upper world, and to Olenos and Lethaea?",
        "options": ["Orpheus", "Eurydice", "Phaedra", "Dido"],
        "correct_answer": "Orpheus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What couple, where the wife boasted about his beauty and the husband tried to take the punishment upon himself, were turned to stone on Mt. Ida?",
        "options": ["Olenos and Lethaea", "Pyramus and Thisbe", "Narcissus and Echo", "Cadmus and Harmonia"],
        "correct_answer": "Olenos and Lethaea"
    },
    {
        "question": "What were Olenos and Lethaea turned into?",
        "options": ["stone", "trees", "animals", "flowers"],
        "correct_answer": "stone"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where were Olenos and Lethaea turned into stone?",
        "options": ["Mt. Ida", "Mt. Olympus", "Mt. Parnassus", "Mt. Etna"],
        "correct_answer": "Mt. Ida"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is compared to violets or poppies or lilies when someone steps on them?",
        "options": ["Hyacinthus", "Adonis", "Tithonus", "Orpheus"],
        "correct_answer": "Hyacinthus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What group of promiscuous women were from Amathus?",
        "options": ["Propoetides", "Nereids", "Muses", "Sirens"],
        "correct_answer": "Propoetides"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where were the Propoetides from?",
        "options": ["Amathus", "Thebes", "Corinth", "Athens"],
        "correct_answer": "Amathus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What horned monsters who guarded an altar of Jupiter Hospes but killed their guests instead of honoring them?",
        "options": ["Cerastae", "Satyrs", "Cyclopes", "Giants"],
        "correct_answer": "Cerastae"
    },
    {
        "question": "What feature did the Cerastae have?",
        "options": ["horns", "wings", "scales", "claws"],
        "correct_answer": "horns"
    },
    {
        "question": "An altar of WHAT god was guarded by the Cerastae?",
        "options": ["Jupiter Hospes", "Apollo", "Neptune", "Mars"],
        "correct_answer": "Jupiter Hospes"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who punished the Cerastae by transforming them into bulls?",
        "options": ["Venus", "Minerva", "Juno", "Diana"],
        "correct_answer": "Venus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Because they already had horns on their head, WHO were transformed into bulls by Venus?",
        "options": ["Cerastae", "Satyrs", "Cyclopes", "Giants"],
        "correct_answer": "Cerastae"
    },
    {
        "question": "Into what were the Cerastae transformed by Venus as punishment for killing their guests instead of honoring them?",
        "options": ["bulls", "pigs", "goats", "dogs"],
        "correct_answer": "bulls"
    },
    {
        "question": "What group denied Venus’s divinity and was punished by being the first prostitutes?",
        "options": ["Propoetides", "Nereids", "Muses", "Siren"],
        "correct_answer": "Propoetides"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who turned the Propoetides into the first prostitutes?",
        "options": ["Venus", "Apollo", "Diana", "Juno"],
        "correct_answer": "Venus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What group became stone because the blood left their face due to their inability to blush and their loss of shame?",
        "options": ["Propoetides", "Satyrs", "Giants", "Cyclopes"],
        "correct_answer": "Propoetides"
    },
    {
        "question": "What did the Propoetides become because the blood left their face due to their inability to blush and their loss of shame?",
        "options": ["stone", "trees", "animals", "flowers"],
        "correct_answer": "stone"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who, seeing the behavior of the Propoetides, decided he hated women and refused to marry?",
        "options": ["Pygmalion", "Orpheus", "Tithonus", "Aeneas"],
        "correct_answer": "Pygmalion"
    },
    {
        "question": "What group caused Myrrha to fall in love with her father Cinyras?",
        "options": ["Furies", "Muses", "Graces", "Nereids"],
        "correct_answer": "Furies"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was caused by the Furies to fall in love with her father?",
        "options": ["Myrrha", "Phaedra", "Leda", "Helen"],
        "correct_answer": "Myrrha"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who justifies her incest to herself by citing animals who do it, and other regions where it’s acceptable for daughters to sleep with their fathers, and wishes she had been born there?",
        "options": ["Myrrha", "Dido", "Jocasta", "Phyllis"],
        "correct_answer": "Myrrha"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is about to hang herself because she wants to commit incest, but is saved by her nurse?",
        "options": ["Myrrha", "Phaedra", "Medea", "Scylla"],
        "correct_answer": "Myrrha"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who celebrates a festival of Ceres, during which she’s not allowed to have sex for nine days?",
        "options": ["Cenchreis", "Phyllis", "Medea", "Dido"],
        "correct_answer": "Cenchreis"
    },
    {
        "question": "What deity's festival does Cenchreis celebrate during which she’s not allowed to have sex for nine days?",
        "options": ["Ceres", "Apollo", "Diana", "Jupiter"],
        "correct_answer": "Ceres"
    },
    {
        "question": "What 2 people's eyes are covered by the constellation Icarius and Erigone?",
        "options": ["Cinyras and Myrrha", "Pyramus and Thisbe", "Narcissus and Echo", "Cadmus and Harmonia"],
        "correct_answer": "Cinyras and Myrrha"
    },
    {
        "question": "What 2 constellations cover the eyes of Cinyras and Myrrha when Myrrha enters his bedroom?",
        "options": ["Icarius and Erigone", "Orion and Pleiades", "Aquila and Delphinus", "Lyra and Cygnus"],
        "correct_answer": "Icarius and Erigone"
    },
    {
        "question": "An owl 3 times makes its ill-omened cries when WHO enters her lover's bedroom?",
        "options": ["Myrrha", "Phaedra", "Dido", "Helen"],
        "correct_answer": "Myrrha"
    },
    {
        "question": "What animal 3 times makes its ill-omened cry when Myrrha enters the bedroom of Cinyras?",
        "options": ["owl", "dog", "crow", "hawk"],
        "correct_answer": "owl"
    },
    {
        "question": "When Cupid gives his mother Venus a kiss, he accidentally wounds her with an arrow, causing her to fall in love with WHOM?",
        "options": ["Adonis", "Perseus", "Hercules", "Aeneas"],
        "correct_answer": "Adonis"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who made the temple of Cybele that Hippomenes and Atalanta sleep in?",
        "options": ["Echion", "Perseus", "Theseus", "Cadmus"],
        "correct_answer": "Echion"
    },
    {
        "question": "What deity's temple does Echion, a Spartoi, make?",
        "options": ["Cybele", "Apollo", "Jupiter", "Venus"],
        "correct_answer": "Cybele"
    },
    {
        "question": "What animal is turned to stone as it tries to attack the head of Orpheus?",
        "options": ["snake", "lion", "bear", "eagle"],
        "correct_answer": "snake"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who turns a snake into stone when it tries to attack the head of Orpheus when it arrives at Lesbos?",
        "options": ["Apollo", "Zeus", "Hermes", "Poseidon"],
        "correct_answer": "Apollo"
    },
    {
        "question": "A snake that tries to attack the head of Orpheus is transformed into WHAT?",
        "options": ["stone", "gold", "fire", "water"],
        "correct_answer": "stone"
    },
    {
        "question": "What Phrygian king had learned the rites of Dionysus from Eumolpus and Orpheus?",
        "options": ["Midas", "Gordius", "Meleager", "Phineas"],
        "correct_answer": "Midas"
    },
    {
        "question": "What 2 men had taught Midas the rites of Dionysus?",
        "options": ["Eumolpus and Orpheus", "Zeus and Apollo", "Hermes and Dionysus", "Ares and Hephaestus"],
        "correct_answer": "Eumolpus and Orpheus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whose rites are taught by Eumolpus and Orpheus to Midas?",
        "options": ["Dionysus", "Apollo", "Athena", "Aphrodite"],
        "correct_answer": "Dionysus"
    },
    {
        "question": "To what region must Peleus go for killing Phocus?",
        "options": ["Trachis", "Thebes", "Argos", "Sparta"],
        "correct_answer": "Trachis"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who transforms into an old woman at night to seduce Chione?",
        "options": ["Apollo", "Hermes", "Zeus", "Apollo"],
        "correct_answer": "Apollo"
    },
    {
        "question": "What does Apollo transform himself into to seduce Chione?",
        "options": ["old woman", "young man", "wolf", "eagle"],
        "correct_answer": "old woman"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is killed by being shot in the tongue by Diana?",
        "options": ["Chione", "Hyacinthus", "Phyllis", "Phaedra"],
        "correct_answer": "Chione"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who shoots Chione in the tongue which kills her?",
        "options": ["Diana", "Apollo", "Artemis", "Hera"],
        "correct_answer": "Diana"
    },
    {
        "question": "On what body part does Diana shoot and kill Chione?",
        "options": ["tongue", "arm", "leg", "chest"],
        "correct_answer": "tongue"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who embraces the dead Chione attempts to console Daedalion?",
        "options": ["Ceyx", "Theseus", "Orpheus", "Jason"],
        "correct_answer": "Ceyx"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whose dead body is embraced by king Ceyx of Trachis?",
        "options": ["Chione", "Diana", "Clytemnestra", "Polyxena"],
        "correct_answer": "Chione"
    },
    {
        "question": "What herdsman shows up to Trachis with a message for Peleus?",
        "options": ["Onetor", "Pan", "Silenus", "Arcas"],
        "correct_answer": "Onetor"
    },
    {
        "question": "For whom did the herdsman Onetor have a message?",
        "options": ["Peleus", "Hercules", "Theseus", "Achilles"],
        "correct_answer": "Peleus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who prepares to go to Apollo’s oracle at Claros since he was disturbed by omens related to his brother’s death?",
        "options": ["Ceyx", "Peleus", "Orestes", "Aeneas"],
        "correct_answer": "Ceyx"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where was there an oracle of Apollo that Ceyx was trying to go to to find out about his brother's death?",
        "options": ["Claros", "Delphi", "Dodona", "Delos"],
        "correct_answer": "Claros"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who had an oracle at Claros that Ceyx was preparing to go to?",
        "options": ["Apollo", "Hermes", "Zeus", "Hades"],
        "correct_answer": "Apollo"
    },
    {
        "question": "What Phlegyan was making Delphi inaccessible until Apollo challenged him to a boxing match in the form of a child and vanquished him?",
        "options": ["Phorbas", "Eurytus", "Antaeus", "Geryon"],
        "correct_answer": "Phorbas"
    },
    {
        "question": "What people is Phorbas, the man who was making Delphi inaccessible, a part of?",
        "options": ["Phlegyans", "Titans", "Giants", "Cyclopes"],
        "correct_answer": "Phlegyans"
    },
    {
        "question": "What city was Phorbas making inaccessible?",
        "options": ["Delphi", "Athens", "Thebes", "Sparta"],
        "correct_answer": "Delphi"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who challenged Phorbas to a boxing match in the form of a child and killed him?",
        "options": ["Apollo", "Hercules", "Theseus", "Ares"],
        "correct_answer": "Apollo"
    },
    {
        "question": "What type of contest did Apollo challenge Phorbas to, where he killed him?",
        "options": ["Boxing", "Wrestling", "Chariot Racing", "Archery"],
        "correct_answer": "Boxing"
    },
    {
        "question": "What form did Apollo take to challenge Phorbas to a boxing match and kill him?",
        "options": ["child", "wolf", "eagle", "old man"],
        "correct_answer": "child"
    },
    {
        "question": "The star Lucifer stays dark that night in mourning of WHOSE death?",
        "options": ["Ceyx", "Phaeton", "Orpheus", "Pyramus"],
        "correct_answer": "Ceyx"
    },
    {
        "question": "What star stays dark on the night of Ceyx death to resemble mourning?",
        "options": ["Lucifer", "Vesper", "Sirius", "Polaris"],
        "correct_answer": "Lucifer"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who sends Iris to visit the house of Somnus and tell him to send Alcyone a dream?",
        "options": ["Juno", "Venus", "Diana", "Hera"],
        "correct_answer": "Juno"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is sent by Juno to visit the house of Somnus and tell him to send Alcyone a dream?",
        "options": ["Iris", "Hermes", "Apollo", "Nike"],
        "correct_answer": "Iris"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who is told by Iris to send Alcyone a dream?",
        "options": ["Somnus", "Hades", "Morpheus", "Zeus"],
        "correct_answer": "Somnus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whose home is doorless lest the creaking of the doors make noise, and is on the same island near the Cimmerians?",
        "options": ["Somnus", "Elysium", "Hades", "Lethe"],
        "correct_answer": "Somnus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who sends Morpheus to visit Alcyone?",
        "options": ["Somnus", "Hades", "Apollo", "Jupiter"],
        "correct_answer": "Somnus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whom does Somnus send to visit Alcyone?",
        "options": ["Morpheus", "Thanatos", "Hypnos", "Phantasos"],
        "correct_answer": "Morpheus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who takes on the form of Ceyx (without the man’s usual splendor, naked, and with wet hair and beard) and describes what happened to Alcyone in her dream?",
        "options": ["Morpheus", "Iris", "Apollo", "Somnus"],
        "correct_answer": "Morpheus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whose form does Morpheus take, without the man’s usual splendor, naked, and with wet hair and beard, when appearing to Alcyone in her dream?",
        "options": ["Ceyx", "Zeus", "Hermes", "Orpheus"],
        "correct_answer": "Ceyx"
    },
    {
        "question": "What bird's nest in the sea remain calm because Aeolus keeps the wind in check?",
        "options": ["Halcyons", "Eagles", "Swans", "Pelicans"],
        "correct_answer": "Halcyons"
    },
    {
        "question": "According to Ovid, a blue snake slithers in a bird's nest and eats 8 baby birds WHERE?",
        "options": ["Aulis", "Delphi", "Troy", "Argos"],
        "correct_answer": "Aulis"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who lives in the center of the world, in a home with thousands of entrances and exits, with voices and whispers going back and forth, accompanied by the likes of Credulitas and Error?",
        "options": ["Fama", "Hades", "Zeus", "Apollo"],
        "correct_answer": "Fama"
    },
    {
        "question": "What general region does Fama live in?",
        "options": ["the center of the world", "the underworld", "Olympus", "the heavens"],
        "correct_answer": "the center of the world"
    },
    {
        "question": "Near what river did Achilles wound Telephus?",
        "options": ["Caicus", "Euphrates", "Tiber", "Achelous"],
        "correct_answer": "Caicus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was wounded near the Caicus river?",
        "options": ["Telephus", "Hector", "Ajax", "Paris"],
        "correct_answer": "Telephus"
    },
    {
        "question": "To prove his spear still works, WHO kills a random Lycian named Menoetes?",
        "options": ["Achilles", "Hercules", "Theseus", "Perseus"],
        "correct_answer": "Achilles"
    },
    {
        "question": "What Lycian is killed by Achilles to prove that his spear still works in a battle against the invulnerable Cycnus?",
        "options": ["Menoetes", "Clytemenestra", "Meleager", "Antilochus"],
        "correct_answer": "Menoetes"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who saw Caeneus' invulnerability and has the idea to beat him to the ground with oak / fir trees?",
        "options": ["Monychus", "Eurytion", "Chiron", "Pholus"],
        "correct_answer": "Monychus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What type of creature was Monychus?",
        "options": ["centaur", "giant", "nymph", "cyclops"],
        "correct_answer": "centaur"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whom did Monychus see, and subsequently kill?",
        "options": ["Caeneus", "Hercules", "Orpheus", "Philoctetes"],
        "correct_answer": "Caeneus"
    },
    {
        "question": "According to Ovid, what type of tree did Monychus and other Centaurs use to kill Caeneus?",
        "options": ["oak tree", "pine tree", "olive tree", "cypress tree"],
        "correct_answer": "oak tree"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who claimed that Caeneus was transformed into a golden bird?",
        "options": ["Mopsus", "Tlepolemus", "Polydorus", "Aeneas"],
        "correct_answer": "Mopsus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Into what was Caeneus transformed?",
        "options": ["golden bird", "silver tree", "bronze statue", "golden statue"],
        "correct_answer": "golden bird"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was transformed into a golden bird?",
        "options": ["Caeneus", "Narcissus", "Aeneas", "Polydorus"],
        "correct_answer": "Caeneus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who complains that his father was snubbed in Nestor's narrative of the Lapiths vs Centaurs, since he had played an important role in defeating the Centaurs?",
        "options": ["Tlepolemus", "Perseus", "Meleager", "Hercules"],
        "correct_answer": "Tlepolemus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whose ashes did Hecuba take with her while being dragged away?",
        "options": ["Hector", "Paris", "Achilles", "Polydorus"],
        "correct_answer": "Hector"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who took Hector's ashes with her while being dragged away?",
        "options": ["Hecuba", "Andromache", "Helen", "Cassandra"],
        "correct_answer": "Hecuba"
    },
    {
        "question": "What does Hecuba leave on Hector's tomb?",
        "options": ["a white hair", "a golden crown", "a piece of cloth", "a silver coin"],
        "correct_answer": "a white hair"
    },
    {
        "question": "On whose tomb did Hecuba leave a white hair?",
        "options": ["Hector", "Paris", "Achilles", "Aeneas"],
        "correct_answer": "Hector"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the father of Telemus?",
        "options": ["Eurymus", "Aeolus", "Oceanus", "Tethys"],
        "correct_answer": "Eurymus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the son of Eurymus?",
        "options": ["Telemus", "Misenus", "Glaucus", "Aeneas"],
        "correct_answer": "Telemus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who saw that as soon as the fish touched the herbs in the grass, they fled back into the sea?",
        "options": ["Glaucus", "Odysseus", "Aeneas", "Misenus"],
        "correct_answer": "Glaucus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What happened to the fish that Glaucus saw when they touched the herbs in the grass?",
        "options": ["they fled back to the sea", "they turned into stone", "they changed color", "they began to sing"],
        "correct_answer": "they fled back to the sea"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who purified Glaucus of any mortal parts that remained?",
        "options": ["Oceanus and Tethys", "Apollo and Artemis", "Zeus and Hera", "Poseidon and Amphitrite"],
        "correct_answer": "Oceanus and Tethys"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was purified of any mortal parts that remained by Oceanus and Tethys?",
        "options": ["Glaucus", "Misenus", "Telemus", "Aeneas"],
        "correct_answer": "Glaucus"
    },
    {
        "question": "How many times did Oceanus and Tethys sing a magical incantation to purify Glaucus?",
        "options": ["9", "3", "7", "12"],
        "correct_answer": "9"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who sang a magical incantation 9 times to purify Glaucus?",
        "options": ["Oceanus and Tethys", "Zeus and Hera", "Apollo and Artemis", "Poseidon and Amphitrite"],
        "correct_answer": "Oceanus and Tethys"
    },
    {
        "question": "What trumpeteer of his did Aeneas bury?",
        "options": ["Misenus", "Polydorus", "Meleager", "Aeneas's father"],
        "correct_answer": "Misenus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the father of Misenus?",
        "options": ["Aeolus", "Poseidon", "Zeus", "Apollo"],
        "correct_answer": "Aeolus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What son of Aeolus was buried by Aeneas?",
        "options": ["Misenus", "Odysseus", "Achilles", "Telemus"],
        "correct_answer": "Misenus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What profession did Misenus have?",
        "options": ["trumpeteer", "warrior", "sailor", "poet"],
        "correct_answer": "trumpeteer"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who buried his trumpeteer Misenus?",
        "options": ["Aeneas", "Odysseus", "Hercules", "Theseus"],
        "correct_answer": "Aeneas"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who grew so decrepit that she became just a voice?",
        "options": ["Cumaean Sibyl", "Echo", "Nymphaea", "Morpheus"],
        "correct_answer": "Cumaean Sibyl"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who passed by the future site of Caieta?",
        "options": ["Aeneas", "Hercules", "Achilles", "Perseus"],
        "correct_answer": "Aeneas"
    },
    {
        "question": "What future site did Aeneas pass?",
        "options": ["Caieta", "Troy", "Rome", "Delphi"],
        "correct_answer": "Caieta"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who will Caieta be named after?",
        "options": ["Aeneas's nurse", "Aeneas's wife", "Aeneas's daughter", "Aeneas's mother"],
        "correct_answer": "Aeneas's nurse"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who did Aeneas meet at Caieta?",
        "options": ["Macareus", "Misenus", "Polydorus", "Glaucus"],
        "correct_answer": "Macareus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who met Macareus at Caieta?",
        "options": ["Aeneas", "Odysseus", "Hercules", "Perseus"],
        "correct_answer": "Aeneas"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whose expedition did Macareus survive?",
        "options": ["Odysseus", "Aeneas", "Hercules", "Theseus"],
        "correct_answer": "Odysseus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What companion of his did Macareus notice among Aeneas's followers?",
        "options": ["Achaemenides", "Misenus", "Telemachus", "Eurytion"],
        "correct_answer": "Achaemenides"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who noticed Achaemenides among Aeneas's followers?",
        "options": ["Macareus", "Odysseus", "Achilles", "Perseus"],
        "correct_answer": "Macareus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who accidentally left Achaemenides behind while fleeing from Polyphemus?",
        "options": ["Odysseus", "Hercules", "Aeneas", "Telemachus"],
        "correct_answer": "Odysseus"
    },
    {
        "question": "While fleeing from whom did Odysseus leave behind Achaemenides?",
        "options": ["Polyphemus", "Scylla", "Charybdis", "Circe"],
        "correct_answer": "Polyphemus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who did Odysseus leave behind while fleeing from Polyphemus?",
        "options": ["Achaemenides", "Misenus", "Telemachus", "Eurytion"],
        "correct_answer": "Achaemenides"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whose ships did Achaemenides see passing by?",
        "options": ["Aeneas", "Odysseus", "Hercules", "Theseus"],
        "correct_answer": "Aeneas"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who saw Aeneas's ships passing by and begged them to take him on?",
        "options": ["Achaemenides", "Misenus", "Polydorus", "Macareus"],
        "correct_answer": "Achaemenides"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who wandered in grief for 6 days after her lover disappeared?",
        "options": ["Canens", "Pomona", "Venus", "Diana"],
        "correct_answer": "Canens"
    },
    {
        "question": "How many days did Canens wander in grief for after Picus's disappearance?",
        "options": ["6", "3", "7", "10"],
        "correct_answer": "6"
    },
    {
        "question": "At what river did Canens whither away while singing?",
        "options": ["Tiber", "Nile", "Po", "Danube"],
        "correct_answer": "Tiber"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who whithered away while singing on the Tiber river?",
        "options": ["Canens", "Venus", "Diana", "Pomona"],
        "correct_answer": "Canens"
    },
    {
        "question": "What herald did Turnus send to Argyripa?",
        "options": ["Venulus", "Aeneas", "Misenus", "Polydorus"],
        "correct_answer": "Venulus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who sent the herald Venulus to Argyripa?",
        "options": ["Turnus", "Aeneas", "Hercules", "Odysseus"],
        "correct_answer": "Turnus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was saved when the Greek fleet shipwrecked off of Cape Caphareus thanks to Minerva?",
        "options": ["Diomedes", "Odysseus", "Achilles", "Agamemnon"],
        "correct_answer": "Diomedes"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who saved Diomedes from death when the Greek fleet crashed off of Cape Caphareus?",
        "options": ["Minerva", "Apollo", "Jupiter", "Neptune"],
        "correct_answer": "Minerva"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of Diomedes's companions said that Venus couldn't do anything more to them after all she'd done?",
        "options": ["Acmon", "Misenus", "Glaucus", "Odysseus"],
        "correct_answer": "Acmon"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whose companion was Acmon?",
        "options": ["Diomedes", "Aeneas", "Odysseus", "Hercules"],
        "correct_answer": "Diomedes"
    },
    {
        "question": "What was Acmon turned into?",
        "options": ["bird", "fish", "tree", "stone"],
        "correct_answer": "bird"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whose hate did Acmon scorn?",
        "options": ["Venus", "Minerva", "Jupiter", "Apollo"],
        "correct_answer": "Venus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whose cave was formerly held by Epimelid nymphs?",
        "options": ["Pan", "Apollo", "Diana", "Hermes"],
        "correct_answer": "Pan"
    },
    {
        "question": "What nymphs formerly held a cave inhabited by Pan?",
        "options": ["Epimelid nymphs", "Nereids", "Muses", "Dryads"],
        "correct_answer": "Epimelid nymphs"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who drove the Epimelid nymphs away from the cave?",
        "options": ["an Apulian shepherd", "Hercules", "Odysseus", "Zeus"],
        "correct_answer": "an Apulian shepherd"
    },
    {
        "question": "What did the Apulian shepherd who drove the Epimelid nymphs away from the caves mock?",
        "options": ["their dancing", "their singing", "their beauty", "their food"],
        "correct_answer": "their dancing"
    },
    {
        "question": "What was the Apulian shepherd turned into?",
        "options": ["wild olive-tree", "pine tree", "oak tree", "stone"],
        "correct_answer": "wild olive-tree"
    },
    {
        "question": "What was the hometown of Turnus that Aeneas destroyed after he wins the war?",
        "options": ["Ardea", "Troy", "Rome", "Carthage"],
        "correct_answer": "Ardea"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who destroyed the town of Ardea after the war with Turnus?",
        "options": ["Aeneas", "Odysseus", "Hercules", "Achilles"],
        "correct_answer": "Aeneas"
    },
    {
        "question": "What rises from the city of Ardea's ashes?",
        "options": ["heron", "eagle", "dove", "phoenix"],
        "correct_answer": "heron"
    },
    {
        "question": "From which city's ashes did a heron rise?",
        "options": ["Ardea", "Troy", "Rome", "Carthage"],
        "correct_answer": "Ardea"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who ordered Numiclus to purify Aeneas?",
        "options": ["Venus", "Jupiter", "Minerva", "Neptune"],
        "correct_answer": "Venus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What river did Venus order to purify Aeneas?",
        "options": ["Numiclus", "Tiber", "Po", "Danube"],
        "correct_answer": "Numiclus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who became the god Indiges after death?",
        "options": ["Aeneas", "Ascanius", "Remulus", "Acrota"],
        "correct_answer": "Aeneas"
    },
    {
        "question": "What god did Aeneas become after death?",
        "options": ["Indiges", "Apollo", "Jupiter", "Mars"],
        "correct_answer": "Indiges"
    },
    {
        "question": "What city did Ascanius, Silvius, Latinus, Alba, Epytus, Capys, Capetus, Tiberinus, Remulus, Acrota, Aventinus, and Proca rule?",
        "options": ["Alba Longa", "Rome", "Carthage", "Troy"],
        "correct_answer": "Alba Longa"
    },
    {
        "question": "What king of Alba Longa was struck by lightning?",
        "options": ["Remulus", "Acrota", "Ascanius", "Capys"],
        "correct_answer": "Remulus"
    },
    {
        "question": "How did Remulus die?",
        "options": ["struck by lightning", "poisoned", "stabbed", "drowned"],
        "correct_answer": "struck by lightning"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the brother of Remulus?",
        "options": ["Acrota", "Ascanius", "Silvius", "Capys"],
        "correct_answer": "Acrota"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the brother of Acrota?",
        "options": ["Remulus", "Ascanius", "Silvius", "Tiberinus"],
        "correct_answer": "Remulus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was sought after by all the satyrs and panes?",
        "options": ["Pomona", "Ceres", "Diana", "Aphrodite"],
        "correct_answer": "Pomona"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was sought after by even Silvanus and Priapus?",
        "options": ["Pomona", "Ceres", "Diana", "Venus"],
        "correct_answer": "Pomona"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who frequently disguised as a reaper, plowman, soldier, and a fisherman to get a glimpse at his liver?",
        "options": ["Vertumnus", "Mercury", "Apollo", "Jupiter"],
        "correct_answer": "Vertumnus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What man, who fought at Troy, was Anaxarete a descendant of?",
        "options": ["Teucer", "Hector", "Aeneas", "Paris"],
        "correct_answer": "Teucer"
    },
    {
        "question": "What woman was the descendant of Teucer?",
        "options": ["Anaxarete", "Hersilia", "Pomona", "Diana"],
        "correct_answer": "Anaxarete"
    },
    {
        "question": "What name is given to the statue which Anaxarete turned into?",
        "options": ["Venus Prospiciens", "Venus Anadyomene", "Venus Victrix", "Venus Callipyge"],
        "correct_answer": "Venus Prospiciens"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who became the statue Venus Prospiciens?",
        "options": ["Anaxarete", "Diana", "Pomona", "Hersilia"],
        "correct_answer": "Anaxarete"
    },
    {
        "question": "What Cypriot city was the statue of Venus Prospiciens put in?",
        "options": ["Salamis", "Paphos", "Amathus", "Kourion"],
        "correct_answer": "Salamis"
    },
    {
        "question": "What deity opened one of the doors to the Sabines?",
        "options": ["Juno", "Venus", "Apollo", "Mars"],
        "correct_answer": "Juno"
    },
    {
        "question": "What deity asked naiads in a cold spring near the gateway of Janus to block the path of the Sabines?",
        "options": ["Venus", "Juno", "Minerva", "Ceres"],
        "correct_answer": "Venus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who did Venus ask to block the path of the Sabines?",
        "options": ["naiads", "dryads", "nymphs", "Fates"],
        "correct_answer": "naiads"
    },
    {
        "question": "Near the gateway of WHICH god did the naiads asked for help by Venus live?",
        "options": ["Janus", "Neptune", "Apollo", "Mercury"],
        "correct_answer": "Janus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What do naiads use to heat the cold spring they're in to the boiling point?",
        "options": ["sulphur and pitch", "fire and brimstone", "salt and heat", "charcoal and lava"],
        "correct_answer": "sulphur and pitch"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whose path did naiads block after overflowing a spring near the gate of Janus?",
        "options": ["Sabines", "Romans", "Greeks", "Trojan allies"],
        "correct_answer": "Sabines"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was visited by Iris and led to the Quirinal?",
        "options": ["Hersilia", "Diana", "Pomona", "Ceres"],
        "correct_answer": "Hersilia"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who visited Hersilia and led her to the Quirinal?",
        "options": ["Iris", "Mercury", "Apollo", "Venus"],
        "correct_answer": "Iris"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was Hersilia deified as?",
        "options": ["Hora", "Pomona", "Venus", "Juno"],
        "correct_answer": "Hora"
    },
    {
        "question": "On which hill was Hersilia deified?",
        "options": ["Quirinal", "Capitoline", "Palatine", "Aventine"],
        "correct_answer": "Quirinal"
    },
    {
        "question": "What fell from the sky, resulting in Hersilia being deified as Hora?",
        "options": ["comet", "thunderbolt", "rain", "fire"],
        "correct_answer": "comet"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who does Pythagoras claim to be in a previous life during the Trojan War?",
        "options": ["Euphorbus", "Hector", "Achilles", "Paris"],
        "correct_answer": "Euphorbus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the father of Euphorbus?",
        "options": ["Panthous", "Hector", "Priam", "Paris"],
        "correct_answer": "Panthous"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was the son of Panthous?",
        "options": ["Euphorbus", "Hector", "Aeneas", "Paris"],
        "correct_answer": "Euphorbus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who claimed to be Euphorbus in a previous life during the Trojan War?",
        "options": ["Pythagoras", "Plato", "Socrates", "Aristotle"],
        "correct_answer": "Pythagoras"
    },
    {
        "question": "What river was made undrinkable after Centaurs washed their wounds there?",
        "options": ["Anigrus", "Styx", "Tiber", "Nile"],
        "correct_answer": "Anigrus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who washed their wounds in the Anigrus river after being defeated by Heracles, making it undrinkable?",
        "options": ["Centaurs", "Giants", "Titans", "Nymphs"],
        "correct_answer": "Centaurs"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which region has a river that has the power to set wood on fire?",
        "options": ["Epirus", "Arcadia", "Boetia", "Macedonia"],
        "correct_answer": "Epirus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What does a river in Epirus have the power to do?",
        "options": ["set wood on fire", "turn things to stone", "heal wounds", "cause floods"],
        "correct_answer": "set wood on fire"
    },
    {
        "question": "What happened to things submerged in a river in the territory of the Ciconians?",
        "options": ["they turned to stone", "they floated away", "they dissolved", "they became invisible"],
        "correct_answer": "they turned to stone"
    },
    {
        "question": "In what tribe's territory did a river turn things submerged in it to stone?",
        "options": ["Ciconians", "Thracians", "Arcadians", "Macedonians"],
        "correct_answer": "Ciconians"
    },
    {
        "question": "What lake cures drunkenness?",
        "options": ["Clitorian lake", "Acheron lake", "Triton lake", "Nereus lake"],
        "correct_answer": "Clitorian lake"
    },
    {
        "question": "What does the Clitorian lake cure?",
        "options": ["drunkenness", "blindness", "fever", "madness"],
        "correct_answer": "drunkenness"
    },
    {
        "question": "What river has the opposite effect of the Clitorian lake?",
        "options": ["Lyncestis River", "Tiber River", "Styx River", "Acheron River"],
        "correct_answer": "Lyncestis River"
    },
    {
        "question": "What river has harmful effects only when drunk at night?",
        "options": ["Styx", "Lyncestis", "Tiber", "Anigrus"],
        "correct_answer": "Styx"
    },
    {
        "question": "When does the Styx have harmful effects?",
        "options": ["at night", "during the day", "at dawn", "at dusk"],
        "correct_answer": "at night"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who saw a clod of earth start moving and transform into a man named Tages?",
        "options": ["an Etruscan farmer", "a Roman soldier", "a Greek merchant", "a Latin priest"],
        "correct_answer": "an Etruscan farmer"
    },
    {
        "question": "Into who did an Etruscan farmer see a clod of earth transform?",
        "options": ["Tages", "Euphorbus", "Aeneas", "Pan"],
        "correct_answer": "Tages"
    },
    {
        "question": "What did Tages teach the Etruscans?",
        "options": ["divination", "farming", "music", "warfare"],
        "correct_answer": "divination"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whom did Tages teach divination?",
        "options": ["Etruscans", "Romans", "Greeks", "Carthaginians"],
        "correct_answer": "Etruscans"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who saw his spear suddenly become a willow tree?",
        "options": ["Romulus", "Aeneas", "Hercules", "Jupiter"],
        "correct_answer": "Romulus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What did Romulus's spear suddenly become?",
        "options": ["a willow tree", "a golden staff", "a serpent", "a laurel branch"],
        "correct_answer": "a willow tree"
    },
    {
        "question": "On which hill did Romulus's spear suddenly become a willow tree?",
        "options": ["Palatine", "Capitoline", "Aventine", "Quirinal"],
        "correct_answer": "Palatine"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who saw horns on his forehead when he looked at himself in a river?",
        "options": ["Cipus", "Romulus", "Aeneas", "Hercules"],
        "correct_answer": "Cipus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What position did Cipus hold?",
        "options": ["praetor", "consul", "tribune", "quaestor"],
        "correct_answer": "praetor"
    },
    {
        "question": "What was the full name of Cipus?",
        "options": ["Genucius Cipus", "Lucius Junius", "Marcus Tullius", "Gaius Sempronius"],
        "correct_answer": "Genucius Cipus"
    },
    {
        "question": "What did Cipus's horns mean he would be?",
        "options": ["a future king of Rome", "a high priest", "a military leader", "a great general"],
        "correct_answer": "a future king of Rome"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who interpreted the sign of Cipus's horns?",
        "options": ["an Etruscan haruspex", "a Roman augur", "a Greek oracle", "a Sibyl"],
        "correct_answer": "an Etruscan haruspex"
    },
    {
        "question": "What does Cipus cover his horns with?",
        "options": ["a laurel wreath", "a golden crown", "a silk veil", "a headband"],
        "correct_answer": "a laurel wreath"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whom does Cipus summon?",
        "options": ["the senate and the people", "the military leaders", "the priests and augurs", "the citizens of Rome"],
        "correct_answer": "the senate and the people"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who does Cipus tell the senate and the people to exile?",
        "options": ["a man with horns on his forehead", "a foreigner", "a traitor", "a political rival"],
        "correct_answer": "a man with horns on his forehead"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who was allowed as much land outside the city as he could plow in one day?",
        "options": ["Cipus", "Romulus", "Aeneas", "Cincinnatus"],
        "correct_answer": "Cipus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whose horns were sculpted on the Porta Rauduscula?",
        "options": ["Cipus", "Romulus", "Aeneas", "Julius Caesar"],
        "correct_answer": "Cipus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where was an image of Cipus's horns sculpted?",
        "options": ["Porta Rauduscula", "Capitoline Hill", "Palatine Hill", "Forum Romanum"],
        "correct_answer": "Porta Rauduscula"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the translation for the Porta Rauduscula?",
        "options": ["bronze gates", "silver gates", "iron gates", "golden gates"],
        "correct_answer": "bronze gates"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who visits a Roman in a dream and tells him to look for a snake like the one wrapped around his staff?",
        "options": ["Aesculapius", "Apollo", "Mercury", "Jupiter"],
        "correct_answer": "Aesculapius"
    },
    {
        "question": "What city's people were deciding whether to let the Romans have Aesculapius?",
        "options": ["Epidaurus", "Athens", "Sparta", "Corinth"],
        "correct_answer": "Epidaurus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whom does Aesculapius tell to look for a snake like the one wrapped around his staff?",
        "options": ["a Roman", "a Greek", "a Latin", "a Carthaginian"],
        "correct_answer": "a Roman"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where do the Romans briefly stop on the way back from Epidaurus?",
        "options": ["Antium", "Puteoli", "Ostia", "Cumae"],
        "correct_answer": "Antium"
    },
    {
        "question": "What group comes out to see the snake god (Aesculapius)?",
        "options": ["Vestal Virgins", "Augurs", "Senators", "Plebeians"],
        "correct_answer": "Vestal Virgins"
    },
    {
        "question": "What god do the Vestal Virgins come out to see?",
        "options": ["Aesculapius", "Apollo", "Mars", "Jupiter"],
        "correct_answer": "Aesculapius"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where does Aesculapius settle in the form of a snake?",
        "options": ["Tiber Island", "Capitoline Hill", "Palatine Hill", "Aventine Hill"],
        "correct_answer": "Tiber Island"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who settles on the Tiber Island in the form of a snake?",
        "options": ["Aesculapius", "Apollo", "Jupiter", "Mercury"],
        "correct_answer": "Aesculapius"
    },
    {
        "question": "What does Ovid say Caesar's best accomplishment was?",
        "options": ["being the father of Augustus", "conquering Gaul", "defeating Pompey", "establishing the empire"],
        "correct_answer": "being the father of Augustus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Being the father of Augustus was whose best accomplishment according to Ovid?",
        "options": ["Caesar", "Augustus", "Pompey", "Marc Antony"],
        "correct_answer": "Caesar"
    },
    {
        "question": "What descendant of hers does Venus unsuccessfully try to save preceding his assassination?",
        "options": ["Caesar", "Aeneas", "Romulus", "Hector"],
        "correct_answer": "Caesar"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who unsuccessfully tries to save her descendant Caesar?",
        "options": ["Venus", "Jupiter", "Minerva", "Diana"],
        "correct_answer": "Venus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who forbids Venus from hiding Caesar in a cloud?",
        "options": ["Jupiter", "Mars", "Apollo", "Mercury"],
        "correct_answer": "Jupiter"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who does Venus try to hide in a cloud?",
        "options": ["Caesar", "Aeneas", "Romulus", "Hector"],
        "correct_answer": "Caesar"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who tries to hide Caesar in a cloud?",
        "options": ["Venus", "Jupiter", "Minerva", "Mars"],
        "correct_answer": "Venus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where does Venus try to hide Caesar?",
        "options": ["in a cloud", "in the underworld", "on a mountain", "in the sea"],
        "correct_answer": "in a cloud"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whose deeds did Jupiter predict?",
        "options": ["Augustus", "Caesar", "Romulus", "Aeneas"],
        "correct_answer": "Augustus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who predicts the deeds of Augustus?",
        "options": ["Jupiter", "Venus", "Apollo", "Mars"],
        "correct_answer": "Jupiter"
    },
    {
        "question": "What did Venus turn Caesar into?",
        "options": ["a comet", "a star", "a serpent", "a bird"],
        "correct_answer": "a comet"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who turned Caesar into a comet?",
        "options": ["Venus", "Jupiter", "Apollo", "Mars"],
        "correct_answer": "Venus"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who does Venus turn into a comet?",
        "options": ["Caesar", "Aeneas", "Romulus", "Hector"],
        "correct_answer": "Caesar"
    },
    {
        "question": "Whom does Ovid pray to have a long life?",
        "options": ["Augustus", "Caesar", "Romulus", "Aeneas"],
        "correct_answer": "Augustus"
    }
]
}